<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A supplication of the Family of Loue (said to be presented into the Kings royall hands, knowen to be dispersed among his loyall subiectes) for grace and fauour Examined, and found to be derogatorie in an hie degree, vnto the glorie of God, the honour of our King, and the religion in this realme both soundly professed &amp; firmly established.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00545</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114625</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849850</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849850</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15022</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00545)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15022)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 790:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A supplication of the Family of Loue (said to be presented into the Kings royall hands, knowen to be dispersed among his loyall subiectes) for grace and fauour Examined, and found to be derogatorie in an hie degree, vnto the glorie of God, the honour of our King, and the religion in this realme both soundly professed &amp; firmly established.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 65, [3] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed[ by H. Lownes] for Iohn Legate, Printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes the supplication.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The families supplication examined and confuted.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Familists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:15022:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <l>Our Heart is the Mind of God moſt high.</l>
                     <l>Our Beeing amiable as the ſweete Lillie.</l>
                     <l>Our faith fullnes Loue and Trueth upright,</l>
                     <l>Is Gods Light, life and Cleernes bright.</l>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15022:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SVPPLICATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON OF THE FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Loue (ſaid to be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Kings royall hands, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en <hi>to be diſperſed among his Loyall</hi> Subiectes) for grace and <hi>fauour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Examined, and found to be derogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>in an hie degree, vnto the glorie of God, the honour of our King, and the Religion in this Realme both ſoundly profeſſed &amp; firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 2. <hi>Ver.</hi> 14.15.</bibl>
               <p>I haue a fewe things againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt them that mainetaine the doctrine of BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAAM &amp;c. Euen ſo haſt thou them, that mainetaine the doctrine of the NICOLAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TANES, which thing I hate.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Iohn Legate,</hi> Printer to the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15022:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15022:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS moſt excellent Maieſtie IAMES the <hi>firſt, by the grace of God King of</hi> England, Scotland, France, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>defender of</hi> the Fayth &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST gracious Soueraigne Lord,<note place="margin">The exordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> where there is publiſhed in a booke written by your Highneſſe, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to your moſt noble Sonne (whome Almightie God bleſſe with much honour, happineſſe, and long life) of a people that are of a vile ſecte among the Anabaptiſts, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Family of Loue, who doe hold and mainetaine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proud, vncharitable, vnchriſtian, and moſt abſurd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions; vnto whome your Highneſſe doth alſo giue the name of Puritanes, affirming in the ſay de booke, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of them (as <hi>Browne, Penrie,</hi> and others) doe accord with them in their foule, erroneous, heady, and fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call opinions, which are there ſet downe at large by your Maieſtie, aduiſing your Royall Sonne (as is moſt meet) to puniſh them if they refuſe to obey the Lawe, and will not ceaſe to ſtirre vp rebellion,</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15022:3"/>
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>THis is the <hi>Families</hi> Exordium; and containeth an heauie and pitious complaint vnto, and of the Kings Maieſtie himſelfe, for that in his booke, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction vnto his moſt noble Sonne, hee tearmeth the <hi>Familie of Loue, a vile Sect amongſt the Anabaptiſts;</hi> and alſo giueth them the title of <hi>Puritans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This goeth to their verie hearts,<note place="margin">The Exordium quare ſome.</note> that they ſhould be ſo ranked, and ſtiled, and that by his Maieſtie, and that in a printed booke; and that divulged in a knowen tongue ouer his dominions; and the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected vnto his royall, and deateſt Sonne, euermore to continue. Hence their quarrell, and contention euen with their King, hidden yet vnder the faire wordes of an humble petition. A memorable Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium or preface.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>NOw gratious Soueraigne,<note place="margin">A Propeſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> becauſe it is meete that your Highneſſe ſhould vnderſtand by their ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and declaration of the truth herein by themſelues, of whom your Maieſtie hath beene thus informed, proſtrate at your Princely ſeete, as true, faithfull, loyall, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſubiects, to all your lawes, &amp; ordinances, ciuil, and politique, ſpirituall and temporall, they with humble hearts do beſeech your Princely Maieſtie to vnderſtand that the people of the <hi>Familie</hi> of <hi>Loue,</hi> or of God, doe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſclaime and deteſt all the ſaid abſurd, and ſelfe-conceited opinions, and diſobedient, and erroneous Sects
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15022:3"/>of the Anabaptiſtes, Browne, Penrie, Puritanes, and all other proude-minded Sectes and hereſies whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, proteſting vpon paine of our liues, that we are not of conſent, nor agreeing with any ſuch brain-ſicke Preachers, nor their rebellious and diſobediet Sectes whatſoeuer; but haue been, &amp; euer wil be truely obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to your Highneſſe, and your lawes, to the effuſion of our blood, and expenſes of our goods and lands in your Maieſties ſeruice, highly lauding Almightie God, who hath ſo gratiouſly, &amp; peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie appointed vnto vs ſuch a vertuous, wiſe, religious, and noble King, and ſo carefull, and vnpartiall a Iuſticer to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne ouer vs, beſeeching him daiely to bleſſe your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with his godly wiſedome, and holy vnderſtanding, to the furtherance of his truth, and godlineſſe, and with all honor, happineſſe, peace, &amp; long life, &amp; to iudge right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betwixt falſe hood, and truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>IN this Section they proteſt that they are not (as the King ſaith they are) a vile Sect, but <hi>The Familie of Loue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt their Protestation.</note> or <hi>of God,</hi> or <hi>Gods Familie;</hi> neither that they doe hold, &amp; maintain (as his Maieſtie hath publiſhed) any, much leſſe <hi>many proud, vncharitable, vnchriſtian, and moſt abſurd opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:</hi> yea they doe vtterly <hi>diſclaime &amp; deteſt al the ſaid abſurd, and ſelf-conceited opinions; as alſo the diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and erroneous Sectes of the Anabaptiſtes,</hi> Browne, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>Puritanes, &amp; all other proud-minded Sects, &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies whatſoeuer, &amp;c.</hi> And therfore that his Highnes both miſconceiueth and miſreporteth of them, good men.</p>
               <p>In which their Proteſtation, hee that ſeeth not his moſt excellent and ſacred Maieſtie moſt odiouſly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15022:4"/>to be traduced, as a publike defamer of Gods people, is verie blinde; and againe, obſeruing ſo much, is not grieued thereat, ſheweth that hee neither carrieth ſound affection vnto his Souereigue, nor tendereth the honour of his Prince.</p>
               <p>Now forſomuch as both his Maieſties book is extant, and this their ſupplication (but more truly infamous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell) in many mens hands, eſpecially of the young ones in this <hi>Family of Loue</hi> (for few elſe can haue ſo much as a viewe thereof, vnleſſe they be of the vulgar ſorte, and withall inclineable to receiue their doctrine (of all others the vnfitteſt to read or heare ſuch dangerous diſcourſes): whereby both the Familiſtes are confirmed in their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar inſtructions, and his Maieſtie by ſuch Libels igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniouſly diſperſed is not a little wounded, it is verie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull ſomewhat to examine the truth of this their proteſtation.</p>
               <p>And becauſe they ſay, how the premiſſes are publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the ſayd booke of the Kings, it ſhall not be amiſſe heere to ſet downe his Maieſties verie words, and the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of them, expreſſed by his royall hand, to the end that it may appeare who is more abuſed, either the <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> who are charged, as there is ſet down by his Highneſſe; or his Maieſtie, thus traduced, and that to his face, by the <hi>Family.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſecond booke therefore of his moſt Fatherly, Kingly and diuine directions vnto the royall Impe of rare hope, Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> his beſt beloued ſonne, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, hauing at large ſet down the diſeaſes of the church, and from his owne experience, declared how the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, all his raigne, and ſome yeares afore, had troubled the quiet of the Scottiſh kingdome &amp; Church; oppoſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15022:4"/>themſelues againſt the throne of Maieſtie; laboured by the peoples fauour, and aſſiſtance, the erection of a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment <hi>Democraticall,</hi> by the ruine of the royall State; and ſought to bring in a parity, &amp; equalitie of all degrees, aſwell into the Common-weale, as Church: in the ende he giueth his aduiſe, and ſayth:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take heede therefore (my Sonne) to ſuch Puritanes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Puritanes to beauoided.</note> 
                  <hi>very Peſtes in the Church and Common-weale: whome no deſertes can oblige; neither oathes or promiſes binde; breathing nothing but ſedition, and calumnies; aſpiring without meaſure, railing without reaſon; &amp; making their owne imaginations (without any warrant of the word) the ſquare of their conſcience. I proteſt before the great God, and ſince I am here, as vpon my Teſtament, it is no place for me to lye in, that ye ſhall neuer find with any Hie-land, or border theeues greater ingratitude, and moe vile lies and periuries, then with theſe Phanatick ſpirits. And ſuffer not the principals of them to brooke your land, if you like to ſit at reſt, except ye would keepe them for trying your patience, as</hi> Socrates <hi>did an euill wife. And for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiue againſt their poiſon, entertaine, and aduance the godly, learned and modeſt men of the Miniſtrie, whom of (God be prayſed) there lacketh not a ſufficient nomber: and by their promotion to Biſhoprickes, and benefices (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulling that vile acte of</hi> Annexation, <hi>if ye finde it not done to your hand) ye ſhal not only banniſh their conceited paritie, whereof I haue ſpoken, and their other imaginary groundes, which can neither ſtand with the order of the Church, nor the peace of a Common-weale, and well ruled monarchie: but alſo ſhall ye reeſtabliſh the old inſtitution of the three Eſtates in parliament, which can no otherwiſe be done: But in this I hope (if God ſpare me dayes) to make
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15022:5"/>you a faire entrie; alwayes where I leaue, followe you my ſteps. And to end my aduiſe anent the Church eſtate, cheriſh no man more then a good Paſtor, hate no man more then a proude Puritane, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe and the like wordes (deſcribing the humours of Puritanes, and raſh headie Preachers, which thinke it their honour, as his ſayd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in his preface to the ſayde booke doth ſay, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with Kings, and perturbe whole Kingdomes) were verie offenſiuely taken of the <hi>Puritan faction</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> againſt which they were vttered, &amp; made them to ſuſpect (or at leaſt in reuenge of the cenſure, to call his Highneſſe profeſſion into queſtion among themſelues, and to make others doubtfull) whether his Maieſtie ſo ſincerely fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured the religion in <hi>Scotland</hi> eſtabliſhed as he did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend.</p>
               <p>And albeit the whole inſtruction, eſpecially the firſt booke therof, and theſe words of his Maieſty aboue men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſecond booke: <hi>Entertaine and aduance the godly, learned, and modeſt men of the Miniſterie, whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (God be prayſed) there lacketh not a ſufficient number.</hi> And againe: <hi>Cheriſh no man more then a good Paſtor,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealeth ſufficiently the ſound, and zealous affection that his Maieſtie beareth vnto true Religion; and may, and do ſatisfie all indifferent men: yet, if poſsible it were, that no ſcruple might reſt in the minde of any men, his Highneſſe voluntarily, and in ample wordes, and fully, further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planed his very inwarde conceites of the faction mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt then</hi> (ſayth his Maieſtie) <hi>as to the name of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Who Puritans.</note> 
                  <hi>I am not ignorant that the ſtile therof doth properly belong onely to that vile ſecte amongſt the Anchaptiſus called the</hi> Family of Loue, <hi>becauſe they thinke themſelus
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15022:5"/>onely pure, and in a manner without ſinne, the onely true Church, and onely worthy to bee participant of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and all the reſt of the World to be but abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the ſight of God. Of this ſpeciall Secte I principally meane where I ſpeake of Puritanes; diuers of them, as</hi> Browne, Penry, <hi>and others, hauing at ſundrie times come in</hi> Scotland, <hi>to ſowe their popple amongſt vs, (and from my heart I wiſh they had lefte no ſchollers behinde them, who by their fruits will in the owne time be manifeſted): and partly indeed, I giue this ſtile to ſuch braine-ſicke, and headie Preachers their diſciples, and followers, as refuſing to be called of that Secte, yet participate too much with their humours, in maintaining the aboue mentioned er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; not onely agreeing with the generall rule of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, in contempt of the ciuill Magiſtrate, and in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to their owne dreames, and reuelations: and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly with this Secte in accounting all men prophane that ſweares not to all their fantaſies, in making for euery particular queſtion of the policie of the Church, as great commotion, as if the article of the Trinitie were called in controuerſie; in making the Scripture to be ruled by their conſcience, and not their conſcience by the Scripture; and he that denies, the leſt iot of their grounds,</hi> Sit tibi tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ethnicus, &amp; Publicanus, <hi>not worthy to enioy the benefit of breathing, much leſſe to participate with them of the Sacraments: and before that any of their grounds be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned, let King, people, law, and all be trode vnder foot. Such holy warres are to be preferred to an vngodly peace: no, in ſuch caſes, Chriſtian Princes are not onely to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted vnto, but not to be prayed for: For Prayer muſt come of Fayth, and it is reueiled to their conſcience, that God will heare no prayer for ſuch a Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15022:6"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Iudge then Chriſtian Reader</hi> (ſayth his Highneſſe) <hi>if I wrong this ſort of people, in giuing them the ſtile of that Secte, whoſe errors they imitate: and ſince they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to weare their liuerie, let them not be aſhamed to borrow alſo their name.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty meaneth by Puritans in his Booke.</note> It is only of this kind of men, <hi>that in this booke I write ſo ſharpely, and whome I wiſh my Son to puniſh in caſe they refuſe to obey the lawe, and will not ceaſe to ſtir vp a rebellion, whom againſt I haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the more bitterly in reſpect of diuers famous Libels, and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſpeeches, ſpread by ſome of them, not onely diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably inuectiue againſt all Chriſtian Princes, but euen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull to our profeſſion &amp; Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in reſpect they are come out vnder colour therof, &amp;c.</hi> So &amp; more to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie which I would the <hi>Family</hi> had fully and at large ſet downe.</p>
               <p>For then it would appeare that his Maieſtie moſt iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſpeaketh of <hi>Puritanes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The kindes of Puritanes.</note> diſtinguiſhing them into two ranks, Sects, &amp; ſorts, principal &amp; leſſe principal: the principall, he ſayth, (&amp; properly called <hi>Puritans</hi>) <hi>are a vile Sect of the Anabaptiſts, called the Family of Loue,</hi> with whom in certain main points, both <hi>Browne, Peury</hi> and others do conioyne: the leſſe principall, are certaine <hi>brain-ſicke &amp; heady Preachers</hi> the diſciples &amp; followers of <hi>Browne, Penry,</hi> and others, in their fantaſticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts and rebellious complottings.</p>
               <p>I dare ſay &amp; affirm, his Maieſty taketh not the <hi>Family of Loue,</hi> to be ſimply <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> nor the <hi>Browniſts</hi> &amp; ſuch like, to be ſimply <hi>Familiſts;</hi> nor the <hi>brain-ſicke Preachers</hi> and their dependants, to be ſimply <hi>Browniſts,</hi> but inſome reſpects, wherin they do all concur. <hi>It is onely of this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter kind of men viz.</hi> the diſciples of <hi>Brown, Penry</hi> &amp; ſuch like that in his booke his Maieſty writeth ſo ſharpely, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15022:6"/>whome he wiſheth his Son to puniſh <hi>in caſe they refuſe to obey the law, &amp; will not ceaſe to ſtir vp rebellion.</hi> And yet his Maieſty taketh the <hi>Family of Loue</hi> to be <hi>Puritanes</hi> and the chiefeſt <hi>Puritanes,</hi> and properly, though not the only <hi>Puritans,</hi> and <hi>a vile Sect among the Annabaptiſts,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit happily they do vtterly diſclaime and deteſt both the rebellious actions of the <hi>braine-ſicke Preachers</hi> in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the giddie opinions of our home <hi>Puritanes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Families</hi> fault is therefore not a little in confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that which his Highneſſe with great iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hath diſtinguiſhed; and in taking his wordes abſolutely to be vttered, which are ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but in a particular reſpect. That the <hi>Familiſts</hi> be <hi>Puritanes</hi> in the latter ſenſe, his Maieſtie ſayth not; and yet that the <hi>Familiſtes be a vile Secte of the Anabaptiſtes,</hi> and of all other the moſt odious <hi>Puritanes,</hi> his Highneſſe doth affirme, and his verdict they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be able to diſproue, though they do proteſt, vow, &amp; ſweare neuer ſo much to be contrarie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>AND becauſe your Maieſtie ſhould haue a perfecte viewe,<note place="margin">A Prochmary</note> or an aſſured perſwaſion of the truth of the ſame our proteſtation: if therfore there be any indifferent man of this kingdom, that can iuſtly touch vs with any ſuch diſobedient, and wicked handling of our ſelues, as ſeemeth by your Maieſties book it hath been<note n="*" place="margin">H. N. hath ſo informed his Highneſſe: ſee the anſwere.</note> informed vnto your Highneſſe (vnleſſe they be ſuch our mortall enemies, the diſobedient <hi>Puritanes,</hi> and thoſe of their headie humors before named, who are much more zealous, religious, &amp; preciſe in the tything of Mint, Annis, and Commin, and in the preferring of ſuch like Phariſaicall and ſelfe cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15022:7"/>outwarde traditions, and groundes or hypocriticall righteouſneſſe, then in the performing of iudgement, mercy, and fayth, and ſuch like true and inward righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which God doth moſt chiefely require, and regard (<hi>Math. 15.15.</hi> &amp;c.); and whoſe malices haue for twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fiue yeares paſt, and vpwardes, and euer ſince, with very many vntrue ſuggeſtions, and moſt fowle errors, &amp; odious crimes (the which wee could ſhewe, if neede were) ſought our vtter ouerthrowe and deſtruction, but that wee haue behaued our ſelues, in all orderlineſſe, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe of life, where we dwell and with whom we haue had to deale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>AFter their proteſtation,<note place="margin">Againſt their Proclamation.</note> now followeth aproclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as it were, for anie indifferent man to come in, &amp; ſay his worſt againſt them, to proue them ſuch indeed, as the King ſayth they are.</p>
               <p>And yet it is to bee marked that of indifferent men, they except againſt diuers; as firſt againſt all ſtrangers whatſoeuer, and next againſt all diſobedient <hi>Puritanes,</hi> their mortall one wies, and ſuch like, whoſe malice they haue had experience of, theſe twenty fiue yeares and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes. A ſtrange thing that men indifferent, whether Strangers or of this Common weale ſhould bee repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as partiall witneſſes; as ſtrange againe is it that their mortall enemies the <hi>Puritanes,</hi> and their fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, ſhould be acknowledged of them to be men indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</p>
               <p>That they doe except againſt <hi>Puritanes,</hi> I could not blame them, being as they ſay, their mortal and auncient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15022:7"/>enemies (as are many mo beſides) had they not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed them, at leaſt ſome of them, to bee men of good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and indifferent: but that they ſhould except a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any indifferent Strangers, without ſhewing proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſe of the ſame, doth argue in my conceipt, that Strangers, eſpecially, <hi>Hollanders, Frize-landers,</hi> and others in <hi>Baſe-Almaigne</hi> would vtter ſtrange things of this <hi>Familie of Loue,</hi> and charge them iuſtly with groſſe wickedneſſe, and impious miſdemeanors, if they ſhould be heard.</p>
               <p>But his Maieſtie, beſides Strangers, and phariſaicall Puritans, hath others no doubt in his Kingdome, which vnfainedly doe perform: both iudgement, mercie, and faith, not placing religion in outward obſeruations, who (enquired after and called foorth) can aduertiſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and the State, both how duetifully towardes their Prince, orderly towarde their neighbours, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly in the Church of God, they haue, and do behaue themſelues.</p>
               <p>In the meane ſpace, till this be knowen (which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not thinke is vtterly vnknowen to his Highneſſe) I wil ſet downe the iudgement of one (euerie way a Stranger to vs) againſt whom notwithſtanding none exceptions, I am ſure will be taken by the <hi>Familie of Loue,</hi> or any of them. For they doe beleeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (if they beleeue his writinges) <hi>hee noe more can erre in whatſoeuer hee ſaith, than could the Prophets of God, or Apoſtles of Chriſt</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>H.N.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Spir. c. 13. §. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>and that before whom, and before the eyes of whoſe heart and ſpirit, not only all their actions, but alſo their verie ſecret counſailes, and cogitations are naked and bare</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ibid. c. 3. §. 3.</note>. This man is <hi>H.N.</hi> himſelfe, that great Prophet, or God rather among the <hi>Familiſtes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15022:8"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Alas</hi> (ſaith <hi>H. N.</hi>) <hi>like as the world together with her wiſe and Scripture-learned are darkened, and blinded in Heart (and deafe in Vnderſtanding) which comprehend not the good being of the Loue, nor yet conſider on anie of all that which God, through the Spirit of his Loue, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: but haue alway a luſt to themſelues, and cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the couetouſneſſe, the voluptuouſneſſe of the fleſh; and the falſe wiſedome, which ſeduced them: euen ſo I haue found many of you (yea almoſt all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>H.N.</hi> his iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Familiſtes his followers.</note> 
                  <hi>which make boaſt of Loue, and talke much thereof; to ſtand in ſuch like caſe: and alſo aduiſedly marked, that yee, vnder the pretenſe or color of the Houſe, or ſeruice of Loue, haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to your ſelues the voluptuouſneſſe of the fleſh</hi> (2. Pet. 2. <hi>b.</hi> Iude. 1. <hi>b.</hi>) <hi>according to the manner of the World, to bee your Freedome, and your own Thoughts of the Good-thinking, according to the Imagination of the Knowledge (like vnto many vnilluminated Scripture learned, and Good-thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wiſe) to be your wiſedome: and haue no regard to the godly life of the gratious word, nor to the Counſell of the Teſtimonies of the holy ſpirit of Loue, &amp; her Seruice. And yet notwithſtanding, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one asketh you, whether ye haue adioyned you to the Loue, or are minded to continue with a good will, by the ſame; yea aunſwere, and ſay expreſly; O yea, we wil cleaue vnto the Loue, and not forſake the ſame in any caſe.</hi> All this ſaith, <hi>H. N.</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Proph. of the Spir. c. 2. §. 7.</note> and that not of a few, but of many <hi>yea almoſt all, of the Familie of Loue,</hi> who haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues the voluptuouſneſſe of the fleſh, to be their <hi>Freedome,</hi> or <hi>Felicitie:</hi> and he citeth both, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>b.</hi> and <hi>Iude.</hi> 1. <hi>b;</hi> as if they were the perſons reſerued vnto the day of iudgement to bee puniſhed, becauſe they walke after the fleſh in the <hi>luſt of vneleaneneſſe, deſpiſe rulers, and ſpeake euill of them that are in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15022:8"/>hauing noe regard of godly life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe of his, and this <hi>Familie</hi> ſaith the ſame <hi>H. N.</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Proph. of the Spir. §. 9.</note>: <hi>verely after ſuch a manner yee are towards the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious word of the Lord, and his ſeruice of Loue, euen like vnto an whore, which after her hearts Good-thinking to a cloaking of her whoredome, chooſeth an husband, &amp; cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleth her ſelfe in marriage vnto him, for that ſhe mought boaſt her as a married wife; &amp; vnder ſuch a couering and boaſting that ſhe hath a husband, committeth whoredome: Seeing that ye in like manner without Chriſt, and againſt Chriſt, although yee make great boaſt of him, committe whoredome, and deale nor walke not according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or requiring of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If others thinke hardly and ſpeake badly of theſe <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſtes,</hi> which are ſtrangers vnto them, and none of their ſocietie; and his Maieſtie tearmeth them <hi>a vile Sect;</hi> let them maruell noe more, ſeeing <hi>H. N.</hi> the oldeſt Father of that <hi>Familie,</hi> and priuie to all their actions and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges taketh them, I meane many, euen <hi>Almoſt all of them,</hi> to bee but an whoriſh company, making the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſſe of the fleſh their freedome, or <hi>ſummum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi> neither let them blame others hence forward as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious to their good manners. For <hi>H. N.</hi> hath taught vs what they are.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>OR, if wee doe varie, or ſwarue from the now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Religion in this Land, either in Seruices, Ceremonies, Sermons, or Sacraments;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15022:9"/>
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>Here would I know what they meane by varying or ſwaruing from the now eſtabliſhed religion in this Land.</p>
               <p>If by varying they vnderſtand any outward &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique diſſenting from the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſtabliſhed,<note place="margin">The Familiſtes, Temporizers.</note> or from the Seruices, Ceremonies, Sacraments and exerciſes of the ſame, by abſenting from the Church, or not frequenting and repairing vnto the ſacred and approued aſſemblies, then ſurely can they not he ſaid to varie from our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and exerciſes at all. For they neither altogether with the <hi>Browniſtes,</hi> nor in any Ceremoniall conſiderations, with the halfe <hi>Browniſts,</hi> the <hi>Puritanes,</hi> refuſe to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with vs in the Seruices, Ceremonies, and other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of our Religion; and ſo they doe, or wil doe, liued they at <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>H. N.</hi> hath taught and willed them<note n="(a)" place="margin">Patterne of the preſ. Temps.</note>: <hi>The Seruices or Ceremonies ſhall not ſaue any one</hi> (ſaith <hi>H. N.</hi>) <hi>without the good nature of Ieſus Chriſt and of his ſeruice of Loue, nor yet condemne any one, in that good nature of IESVS CHRIST, nor in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Loue</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">3. <hi>Refrein.</hi> §. 6.</note>.</p>
               <p>Hence it is that they neither accuſe nor blame any folke for their religion, whether the Miniſters of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Church, or in any other (<hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and reformed Church) which miniſter or vſe the Ceremonial Seruices<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 2.</note>: prouided that they hold them ſtill, and ſuffer the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts</hi> to be quiet, and encreaſe: neither ſtriue they at all (whereſoeuer they reſide) nor varie with any one about Religion<note n="(d)" place="margin">Patern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the preſ. Temps.</note>. But this doth not extenuate their fault, but aggrauate their offence, for that they are pliable and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15022:9"/>to all religions, Seruices and times, for their owne eaſe, and aduantage, and to ſhunne perſecution and trouble, which they will not ſuffer, come of religion what will.</p>
               <p>But if by varying from the now eſtabliſhed religion in this Land, &amp;c. they meane howe in their iudgement they condemne, and doe not approue the religion, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, Ceremonies, and Sacraments ratified by the hie, and lawfull authoritie of this Church, as wherein,<note place="margin">The Familiſts moſt capitall enemies vnto ſound &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Seruice</hi> of their <hi>Loue,</hi> or miniſtrie of <hi>H. N.</hi> his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, God is not delighted, and whereby Chriſtians pleaſe not the diuine Maieſty one whit, but rather irritate and offend him; then ſurely they doe more varie from the religion, Seruices, Ceremonies, and Sacraments of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than doth any <hi>Browniſt,</hi> or <hi>Puritane,</hi> or other aduerſarie of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> whatſoeuer. For howſoeuer they ſhowe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues obedient, and externally conformable by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing vnto our Churches, frequenting of Sermons, vſing the Sacramentes, and the like: yet in their hearts and minde, both preſent and abſent, either as childiſh, they deride; or as impious, they condemne them all.</p>
               <p>Witneſſe <hi>H. N:</hi> who ſpeaking of vs, and whoſoeuer elſe bee not of his <hi>Familie,</hi> (whom they imagine to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorne in the land of ignorance) <hi>They build</hi> (ſaith hee in ſcoffing and odious manner) <hi>They build diuerſe common houſes, which they name Gods houſes. And they occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie there manie-manner of fooliſhneſſe, or taken on Seruices, which they name Religions, or Gods ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to waue or hold forth ſome thing before the ignorant people, to a ſtay of the conſent ariſing out of their ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15022:10"/>conſciences, whereby their might ſet their fooliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences at peace</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>H.N.</hi> Spirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, c. 5. §. 1.</note>.</p>
               <p>Which our meetinges and Seruices, elſewhere hee calleth <hi>falſe Exerciſes or vſages</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>H.N.</hi> 1. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort. c. 16. §. 2.</note>, <hi>which heare a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewe, wherewith many ignorant people, that knowe not any difference betweene the true, and the falſe light, become ſeduced and deceiued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in another place: <hi>Therefore cannot the Man (whileſt that he is not yet wholly Godded, in one ſpirit of the godly Being with God) occupie, or vſe any manner of Freedome, that is falſer, wickeder, abſurder, ſeducinger, arroganter, nor horribler againſt God &amp; his vpright Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, nor yet daungerfuller, nor diſtructionabler to the children of men, than this: Namely, that any man ſhould become ſo arrogant, and free, or vnbound of Hart, that he, out of an appeaſed Conſcience or contented Hart, ſhold dare to teach, or ſet forth any thing, through the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the knowledge (whether he then haue taken on the ſame,</hi> Out of the learnedneſſe of the Scriptures, <hi>or out of his good thinking wiſedome) as a Word or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of the Lord: or yet to iuſtitute any Serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> Out of the letre of the Scripture, <hi>accordinge to his good thinkinge, and ſo to plucke or make ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the hearts of men, to deſtruction, thereunder. So H. N.</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Ibid. §. 14.</note>.</p>
               <p>And further: <hi>No man</hi> (ſaith <hi>H. N.</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Ibid. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>can rightly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truth of the holy Scriptures, nor according to the ſpirituall vnderſtanding of the godly wiſedome, deale-in or vſe the true Gods ſeruices, nor the ſeruices of the holy word (it becommeth not like wiſe that any man</hi> (ſaith <hi>H. N.</hi>) <hi>ſhould take-in hand to buſie himſelfe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about) but onlie the illuminated Elders in the godlie wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15022:10"/>which walke in the Houſe of</hi> Loue <hi>&amp;c. &amp; are cue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo Godded with God, or incorporated to God, in all</hi> Loue. <hi>With whom alſo God in one Being, and power of his holy ſpirit, is hominified, or become Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then (obſerue the execrable ſpirit of theſe men) <hi>Therfore it is aſſuredly, all falſe and lies, ſeducing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, what the vngodded or vnilluminated Men, out of the imagination or riches of their knowledge, and out of their learnedneſſe of the Scriptures, bring-forth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, preach and teach. They preach indeede the Letter, and the Imagination of their knowledge: but not the word of the liuing God.</hi> All this hath <hi>H. N:</hi> their prophet<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ibid. §. 17.18.</note>; which well may ſhew that the bodies of his <hi>Familiſtes</hi> may be in our Churches, and at Seruice, Sermons, and Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, but their harts doe loath whatſoeuer they doe either ſee, or heare, though it be neuer ſo firmely groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; apparantly deriued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods written word, if the ſame either proceede not, neither be vttered by the deifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Elders of the <hi>Familie,</hi> or ſome one of them; yea they take not God any where to be truely ſerued, but in their priuate meetings, and among themſelues.</p>
               <p>Hence: <hi>Our God of Loue is the true liuing God</hi> (ſay they) <hi>&amp; beſides him there is no God more, and his Gods ſeruice, which we miniſter vnder the obedience of his Loue, is the true ſafe-making Gods ſeruice, and beſides the ſame there is not any Gods ſeruice more, neither in Heauen nor Earth</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Fid el. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar. c. 4. §. 11</note>.</p>
               <p>This, without producing further teſtimonies either forraigne or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues, may ſuffice to proue that they varie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the now eſtabliſhed religion in this land, both in the Seruices, Ceremonies, Doctrine, &amp; Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the ſame; al which in their iudgements they diſallow, except,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15022:11"/>which is not credible, they condemne the iudgement of <hi>H. N.</hi> and other their Illuminate Elders, touching the ſame, who haue publiſhed theſe their concepts to the open world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>OR haue publikely ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or inueighed either by word, or wrighting againſt our late Soueraigne Princes gouernment, in caſes ſpirituall or temporal, the let vs bee reiected for ſectaries, and neuer receiue the benefite of ſuiects.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>IT cannot bee denied, but the <hi>Puritanes,</hi> I meane the Engliſh faction (whatſoeuer the Scottiſh haue done, whereof onely his Maieſtie ſpeaketh) haue publikely ſpoken and inueighed, aſwell by word as writing, againſt our late Princes authoritie in caſes ſpirituall. <hi>Penrie</hi> ſaid plainely that her gouernment was traiterous to the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of our Sauiour Chriſt<note n="(a)" place="margin">Penry Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plic.</note> and thereſt, not ſo far gon as he, tooke her not, as neither doe they our now King, to be any officer at all of the Church.</p>
               <p>I finde not the <hi>Familie</hi> euer publikely depraued her Highneſſe gouernment, either ſpiritual or temporall, and verie bad men they, and moſt vngrateful if they ſhould; diuerſe of the chiefeſt among them receauing yearely both countenance, and maintenance from her Princely coffers, being her houſholde ſeruants. But this clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them noe whit from being <hi>Sectaries</hi> euen in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect mentioned. For in their publike writinges they ſpeake baſely, and inueigh odiouſly againſt all Princes,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15022:11"/>gouernment, Magiſtracy, and eminencie whatſoeuer, ſpirituall and temporall,<note place="margin">The Familistes condemn all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minencie.</note> and therefore againſt our late Princes gouernement in caſes not onely ſpirituall with the <hi>Puritanes,</hi> but temporall to, with the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among the excellencies of this people, this louely people the <hi>Family of Loue</hi> (for ſo doe they ſtile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues), the leaſt is not, that among them there is no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterfull dominion; there raigneth no man ouer other<note n="(b)" place="margin">H. N. <hi>Spirit: land. c.</hi> 34. §. 8.</note>; they haue no heads nor Kings, which <hi>are borne of the fleſh and bloude of ſinne</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 38. §. 1.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is well pleaſing</hi> (ſayth N. H.) <hi>that the one man of God, Lordeth not ouer the other, neither that the one be the others bond-ſeruant</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 37. §. 9.</note>.</p>
               <p>And as they pleaſe God in that they exerciſe no ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie, but are equall in degree among themſelues; <hi>all Kings,</hi> and a kingdome of Kings<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 38. §. 4</note>: ſo they terme a King, <hi>the ſcum of ignorance</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. §. 14</note>; and deeme it an abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing in the eyes of God for men to Lord ouer each other, and tearme ſuch perſons <hi>Bond-ſeruants</hi> and <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue-ſlaues</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 38. §. 5</note>. Laſt of all they haue Prophecies, that all Maieſties, Dominions, Powers, and gouernments what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, ſhall<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 49. §. 1</note>, and make prayers, that they may<note n="(i)" place="margin">1. <hi>Exhort. c.</hi> 17. §. 6.</note>, ſubmit themſelues vnto the ſeruice of <hi>Loue</hi> (euen as the <hi>Puritanes</hi> would haue <hi>Kings to ſubmit their Scepters, to throw downe their crownes before the Church, yea and to licke vp the dust of the feet of the church</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">T. C. 1. <hi>Reply p.</hi> 144.</note>, and yielde obedience vnto the presbiterie<note n="(l)" place="margin">Eccleſ. diſcip. p. <hi>165.</hi>
                  </note>; and alſo that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as Kings, and onely Kings ſhall euerlaſtingly liue and raigne<note n="(m)" place="margin">H N. <hi>Prou. ca.</hi> 1. §. 18. <hi>Fidel. declar. c.</hi> 4. §. 5. <hi>Praph. of the Spir. c.</hi> 19. §. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> yea and doe raigne vpon the earth<note n="(n)" place="margin">Proph. of the Spir. c. <hi>19. §. c.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>It is therfore apparantly, and from their own books &amp; writings ſufficiently, without other needleſſe demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15022:12"/>proued, that the <hi>Family</hi> is a Secte moſt vile, both varying in Seruices, Ceremonies, Doctrine, and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, from the Religion now eſtabliſhed in this land; and openly inueigh againſt all gouernment of Kings, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, ſpirituall, and temporall; ſighers and ſeekers for a paritie and commixtion of all ſtates: and therefore whatſoeuer they doe, not worthie to receiue the benefit, and freedome due to loyall and good Subiects.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>ONly,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation.</note> right gratious Soueraigne, we haue read certain bookes, brought forth by a Germane, Author, vnder the characters of <hi>H. N.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>HItherto their Proclimarie. Now enſueth a narration. It is much to bee lamented that a promiſcuous rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of all writings, hand ouer head, is permitted vnto all men; the lamentable effectes whereof we haue, and ſee, in this <hi>Family of Loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet I would they had but onely read, and not ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, followed, and applauded theſe bookes, as the very meſſage and oracles of God from Heauen; neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in the darke exerciſes, and Conuenticles of the ſayd <hi>Family.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The time was when the letters H. N. were thought to ſignifie no cedrtaine man, but either the <hi>heauenly nature,</hi> or <hi>Homo Nouus, a newe,</hi> or renewed man: or which A.O. doth in the <hi>Reuelation</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Let of the Fam.</note>: but now he is acknowledged here to be a <hi>Germane Auctor;</hi> and was, though they ſay
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15022:12"/>not ſo much (as, by letters vnto my ſelfe from <hi>Embden,</hi> I can ſhew) by trade a Mercer of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in <hi>Holland:</hi> which courſe of life it had been a bleſſed thing for Gods Church he had ſtill followed, and neuer giuen his minde to the writing of bookes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>WHo affirmeth their that he is prepared, choſen,<note place="margin">Of H. N.</note> and ſent of god to miniſter, &amp; ſet forth the moſt holy ſeruice of the loue of God, and Christ, or of the holy Ghoſt, vnto the children of men, vpon the vniuerſal earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVHat they ſay of</hi> H. N. <hi>he affirmeth euery whit of himſelf, if his owne teſtimonie, without prooſe or warrant, be of any validitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In his Prouerbs:</hi> The God of heauen,<note place="margin">H. N. a moſt impious and blaſphemous magnifier of himſelfe.</note> as the Father himſelfe, is come downe: and bringeth, in the ſeruice of Loue, himſelfe, with his Chriſt and holy Ghoſt, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that which with him is Gods, vnto his obedient Man, <hi>H.N.</hi> And Goding the ſame with him, he hath Manned him with the ſame<note n="(a)" place="margin">H.N. Prouerbs. c. 8. §. 3</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In his Prophecie</hi> of the Spirit, <hi>he termeth himſelfe:</hi> Gods elected Miniſter<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Proph. c.</hi> 13. §. 8.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the foreſayd booke of his Prouerbs, he hath theſe words:</hi> The Lord, out of his mercifull loue, raiſed-up the gracious word, according to his promiſes, and elected <hi>H.N.</hi> thereto, for to miniſter the ſame &amp;c.<note n="(c)" place="margin">H. N, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs. c. 1. §. 6.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And in this Prouerbs againe:</hi> Through which gracious word, and <hi>N.N.</hi> God reuealed <hi>(ſayth he)</hi> the appearing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15022:13"/>of the comming of Chriſt, and the newe day of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement, as alſo the flowing foorth of his holy Spirit of loue to the awaking and raiſing vp of all his holy-ones, out of ſleepe, to their glorious Lordlineſs with Ieſus Chriſt, and to an euerlaſting faſt-ſtanding Kingdome of the godly Maieſtie vpon earth, according to his promiſes.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ibid. §. 17.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And afterward:</hi> Thus hath God declared with <hi>H.N.</hi> the eight thorough-breaking of his true light vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth wherein the Lord, the God of heauen, restered the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Kingdome with his garniſhing, together with all that which God hath ſpoken from the beginning of the World, through the mouth of his holy Prophets &amp;c.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ibid. §. 18.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In his exhortation,</hi> God hath illuminated him <hi>(he ſaith)</hi> with his light, for to illuminate, or giue light to them that dwell yet in darkneſſe vpon the earth<note n="(f)" place="margin">1. Exhor. c. 19 §. 8.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And finally in his firſt Epiſtle:</hi> All people are called, and friendly bidden, through <hi>H. N.</hi> to the repentance for their ſinne, &amp;c. Not alone with his calling, but alſo with all the Scriptures heauenly Teſtimonies, and ſpirituall voyces of the Eternall Truth which are gone forth from the holy ſpirit of loue, and brought to light through <hi>H. N.</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">1. Epiſt. or Cri. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ce. c. 1. § 1.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And why all this? but to the ende that (as himſelfe aduiſeth)</hi> the young ones in the Family ſhould not diſtruſt, nor ſuſpect any manner of euill, or vnwiſedome by him; nor yet in any wiſe perſwade themſelues, that the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, Documents, and inſtructions, which are taught or ſet forth before them, by him the Father of the <hi>Family of Loue,</hi> or oldeſt elder, are too childiſh, or too vnwiſe, for the to follow after<note n="(h)" place="margin">1. Exhort. c. 13. §. 11.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the childe of God muſt alwaies haue in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15022:13"/>that many falſe Prophets are gone into the world: and therfore is not to belieue whatſoeuer is affirmed, but trie the ſpirits whether they are of God. Becauſe men</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not the loue of the truth, that they may be ſaued, God will ſend them ſtrong deluſion that they ſhall belieue lies, that they may be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, which belieued not the truth, but had pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe<note n="(i)" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. V. 10.11.</note>:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The more</hi> H. N. <hi>boaſteth of himſelf that he is illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from aboue, the leſſe is he to be credited, the more to be ſuſpected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let him proue his preparation, his election, vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and generall Apoſtleſhip from Gods word (which he ſhall neuer doe); or let him be accurſed: yet a becauſe he arrogateth to himſelfe the diuine nature, and moſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically and blaſphemouſly auoucheth, that whatſoeuer the Prophets haue foretold are fulfilled in him and the like; and all this to the end that his idle reuelations, cloaked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his</hi> Loue-ſeruice, <hi>may the more ſlily enter into the mindes of wel willing and good meaning people: hold him, and all that hold with, and applaud him, and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticall ſpeculations, euermore accurſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>O Out of which Seruice, or writings we be taught all dutiful obedience<note n="*" place="margin">Vntrue.</note> towards God, and Magiſtrates;<note place="margin">The ſeruice of Loue.</note> and to liue a godly, and honeſt life; and to loue God aboue all things, and our neighbours as our ſelues, agreeing therein with all the holy Scriptures as wee vnderſtand them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15022:14"/>
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>ALL this tendeth to the raiſing vp of credit to <hi>H. N.</hi> &amp; his writings: which ſheweth of what ſpirit theſe men are.</p>
               <p>In their <hi>Courtly deuiſe</hi> (inſcribed vnto the laſt Earle of <hi>Leceſter</hi>) they let not to ſay, that <hi>were all the books of</hi> H. N. <hi>rightly conſidered of with indifferencie, ſo ſhould they be found Aſſiſtants in all to the Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and no hinderers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here I take which they grant, that the holy Scriptures teach all theſe things: next that the religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is ſound, and euery way good and true.</p>
               <p>But that the <hi>Seruice of Loue</hi> &amp; the writings of <hi>H. N.</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; indeed ſo teach as they would beare his Maieſtie in hand, I cannot thinke for diuers reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They hold: <hi>That neither before, nor without their moſt holy Seruice of Loue, &amp;c. the true light hath not been ſet forth, miniſtred, nor taught: &amp; that there ſhal likewiſe no other light nor cleerenes, that can be true, appeare nor yet come hereafter, but the light of loue</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">H. N. 1. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r. doct. c.</hi> 16. §. 10</note>: which is the new doctrine deuiſed by <hi>H. N.</hi> &amp; that we ſo condemne.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They teach, that, <hi>it is aſſuredly al falſe, &amp; lies, ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing &amp; deceitful, that the vngodly or vnilluminated Men, out of the imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or riches of their own knowledge, &amp; out of their learnedneſſe of the Scriptures, bring forth, inſtitute, and teach</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 17.</note>. Then is not <hi>H. N.</hi> his doctrine &amp; Seruice of Loue, grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon the written word of God, but vpon I know not what viſions, &amp; Anabaptiſticall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations: and therefore to be held moſt execrable.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15022:14"/>
               <p> Thirdly, they ſay <hi>There is nothing more needfull to the man at the firſt, where-to enter into life; then that he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf vnder the obedience of loue (meaning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of <hi>H. N.</hi>) &amp; ſo become taught in the Seruice of Loue, for to vnlearne againe al what he hath taken on and learned to himſelfe</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Spir. land. c. <hi>56 §. 7.</hi>
                  </note>: which counſayle of vnlearning is rife, and euery where, &amp; as it were the firſt thing deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the <hi>Nouices</hi> in the Loues ſeruice<note n="(d)" place="margin">H. N. exhort. c. 13. §. 9. Cri. voice c. 1. §. 7.</note>: which mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſteth their religion to be newe and ſingular; when the doctrine in our Churches taught and embraced muſt all be vnlearned, and abhominable and corrupt, for the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of theirs, which they vaunt to be celeſtiall.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, becauſe they may not talke of their ſecrets ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet vtter their myſteries, ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, or nakedly in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their young children &amp; diſciples<note n="(e)" place="margin">H. N. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs. c. 22. §. 15.</note>; that is (as <hi>H. N.</hi> ſayth) <hi>til they haue attained the age of</hi> 30 <hi>yeares, and are come to their manly age, and haue beardes</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 21. §. 1.</note>. They might and would talke of their ſecrets, might their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, and myſteries abide the hearing of godly &amp; modeſt perſons, as Gods holy word, and our doctrine, deriued from the ſacred Scriptures, will.</p>
               <p>Laſt of al, becauſe the <hi>Seruice of Loue,</hi> and books of <hi>H. N.</hi> ſo and none otherwiſe make to the aduancement of godlineſſe and furtherance of virtue, then they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Scriptures. And indeed the make od interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Gods word, turning light into darkeneſſe; truth into falſehood; hiſtories into allegories; and ſound religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into fancies of men.</p>
               <p>But as others vnderſtand them, they tend to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting of true religion, and ouerthrowe of Gods houſe, which is the Church of God, for the erecting of a <hi>newe Family,</hi> whereof they take their name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15022:15"/>
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>AGainſt which auctor, and his books, wee neuer yet heard, nor knew any law eſtabliſhed in this realm by our late gracious Souereigne, but that we mought read the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without offence: whoſe writings wee ſuppoſe vnder your Highneſſe correction, your Maieſtie hath yet neuer ſeen, or peruſed heard of by any indifferent, nor true information.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>IT Is well knowne there be lawes, canons, and iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt erroneous and infectious books: and that Proclamations houe come out expreſly againſt <hi>H. N.</hi> and his ſcandalous inuentions.</p>
               <p>When there be lawes againſt <hi>Sect-maſters</hi> and <hi>Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes,</hi> bee there no lawes, ſhall we thinke, againſt <hi>H. N.</hi> and his bookes?</p>
               <p>Scarſe had I proceeded thus farre in this examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but vpon ſearche I founde a paper, which many yeares hath lyen by mee in my priuate ſtudie, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a forme of abiuration offered by the Lords of the late Queene ELIZABETHS moſt honorable priuie Counſayle, vnto certaine perſons ſuſpected to fauour the vile Hereſies of <hi>H. N.</hi> which forme vvas this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer teacheth that the dead which are fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe in the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An abiuration tendred vnto the Familiſtes, the tenth of October. An. 1580 by ten of the Lords of Q. Elizabeths priuy Counſel.</note> 
                  <hi>riſe vp in this day of his iudgement, and appeare vnto vs in godly glorie, which ſhal henceforth liue in vs euerlaſtingly with Chriſt, and raigne vpon the earth, is a deteſtable Hereticke.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:15022:15"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>But</hi> H. N. <hi>teacheth ſo: Euang. c.</hi> 37. <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore</hi> H. N. <hi>is a deteſtable Heretike.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer teacheth that to be born of the Virgin</hi> Marie <hi>out of the ſeede of</hi> Dauid <hi>after the fleſh, is to be expounded of the pure doctrine out of the ſeede of Loue, is a deteſtable Hereticke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But</hi> H. N. <hi>teacheth ſo: Document: ſent: c.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore</hi> H. N. <hi>is a deteſtable Hereticke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer teacheth that Ieſus Chriſt is come againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs according to his promiſe, to the ende that they all which loue God, and his righteouſneſſe, and Chriſt, and his perfect Being, might preſently enter into the true Reſt, which God hath prepared from the beginning for his his elect, and inherit the euerlaſting life, is a deteſtable Hereticke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But</hi> H. N <hi>teacheth ſo: Euang. c.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore</hi> H. N. <hi>is a deteſtable Hereticke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nauing examined theſe reaſons with the bookes of</hi> H. N. <hi>wee doe finde that in truth hee holdeth theſe hereſies, and we thinke in our hearts, and of our owne knowledge affirme that</hi> H. N. <hi>is in theſe hereſies a deteſtable Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke: Promiſing faithfully before God and your Honors neuer hereafter to haue any dealing with his bookes, and doctrine nor to go-about to bring any to the loue, liking, or reading of them. And that we now ſpeake is the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our hearts, as wee looke for mercie at his hands which ſearcheth the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Would her Maieſties Councell miniſter this Abiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration vnto theſe <hi>Familiſtes,</hi> euen of her owen <hi>Familie,</hi> had they noe law, nor authoritie ſo to doe? Or would the ſaide Courtiers (as before their <hi>Honors</hi> they did) abiure theſe <hi>Hereſies,</hi> if both the ſaid hereſies had not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15022:16"/>in the bookes of <hi>H. N.</hi> and themſelues by Lawe compellable either to abiure, or abide the puniſhment due for obſtinate <hi>Heretickes?</hi> And was there <hi>Lawe</hi> then, <hi>viz. Anno.</hi> 1580. (for in that yeare, and ſo long agoe was this donne) and is there noe Lawe now? Haue they not heard, nor knowen of theſe things by lawfull authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie performed, which were both heard andmade knowen both in Court and Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie; the parties ſome of them, and the cheifeſt yet liuing and in Court, which ſo abiured; &amp; their Children in right auncient place about his Maieſty, before whome they abiured?</p>
               <p>But haue they not heard, nor knowen (as they pretend) of any <hi>Lawe</hi> eſtabliſhed in this Realme againſt <hi>H. N.</hi> and his bookes, by our late gratious <hi>Soueraigne?</hi> Then pray wee vnto God, that they may both heare, and knowe ſome lawe to bee eſtabliſhed againſt them by our nowe raigning, and gratious Soueraigne the King.</p>
               <p>The reſt of this ſection, that his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> (as they feare not to ſay) <hi>neuer yet hath ſeene, or peruſed the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of</hi> H. N. <hi>nor ſomuch as heard of them by any indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, or true information, are words derogatorie in an high degree</hi> to his Maieſties honour; becauſe both his Highneſſe hath affirmed vpon his knowledge the <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes to be a vile ſect of Anabaptiſtes</hi> (yeelding inuincible reaſons of his certaine knowledge, which are aboue ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified), and they ſay his Maieſtie neuer yet ſawe nor peruſed, nor ſo much as heard of <hi>H. N.</hi> his writinges, by any indifferent and true information; in the which the points wherewith hee chargeth them, are moſt true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contained.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15022:16"/>
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>FOr the ſaide <hi>H. N.</hi> in all his doctrine and writings (being as we are crediblie enformed, as much matter in volum, if they were all compiled together, as the whole Bible containeth) doth<note n="*" place="margin">Vntrue.</note> neither take part with, nor write againſt any particular partie, or companie whatſoeuer, as naming them by their names, nor yet prayſe or diſpraiſe any of themy by name<note n="*" place="margin">Vntrue: Hee magnifieth the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>THis vain boaſting of the bulke of <hi>H. N.</hi> his writings is verie vſuall among the <hi>Familiſtes.</hi> About thirtie yeares agoe, mine eares heard his diſciples much bragge of the multitude of <hi>H. N.</hi> his bookes: as if his greate paines in writing were argument ſtronge enough to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce men to the liking of his opinions.</p>
               <p>Which if it beeſo, then haue the Papiſtes a ſtronge reaſon that the trueth is with them on their ſide: the monkes and Friars of whoſe Religion hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed infinite paines in writinge, and compoſing of bookes.</p>
               <p>Then haue wee (whoſe doctrine and religion, deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and drawen from Gods word, as Scripture learning the <hi>Familiſtes</hi> (labour to ſupplant) the truth; and not the <hi>Familiſtes,</hi> to whom for multitude of writinges, they are not comparable: ſome one of vs (as <hi>Caluin</hi>) hauing writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſo much as noe one man eitherin theſe, or our Fathers daies hath done the like<note n="(a)" place="margin">Beza. in vit. Cal.</note>; <hi>Muſculus,</hi> and <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and euerie of theſe, hath written more then any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15022:17"/>man can read in many ſcore of yeares<note n="(b)" place="margin">Bodin. in method. hiſt. c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>: which <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> compoſed ſo many Epiſtles and Letters, as gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together would neere loade two Cartes or Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eraſ. catal. Luc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b.</note>. And therefore equall many Bibles in bulke and bigneſſe.</p>
               <p>And could not the heretickes in all ages ſay as much for their founders, as the <hi>Familiſtes</hi> here doe of <hi>H.N. viz.</hi> that their bookes were many, and themſelues, as ſtudious and painefull in writing of diſcourſes, for the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their inuentions, as euer the true and faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God were, or bee, for the implanting of the truth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Manes,</hi> that Arch-hereticke and great grand Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>H. N.</hi> his errors, was the Father of ſundrie and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers bookes<note n="(d)" place="margin">Epiphan.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Photius,</hi> that peſtilent <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> wrote very manie dſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes both in the Greeke &amp; Latine tongue<note n="(e)" place="margin">Vnicent. Lir. aduerſ. haereſ.</note>, for the propagation of his damnable doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſilides,</hi> that hell-hound compiled more then 24. vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes<note n="(f)" place="margin">Eale myſt. of iniquitie.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Appollinaris,</hi> filled the whole world with his blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous pamphlettes<note n="(g)" place="margin">Baſil. magn.</note>.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Tatianus</hi> (not inferior to any of the reſt, not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny elſe, except perhaps to <hi>H. N.</hi> for impietie) his bookes were infinite and innumerable<note n="(h)" place="margin">Euſeb. eccleſ. hiſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>Which writings notwithſtanding were not ſo applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by ſome, as they were abhorred of others: nor ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in times paſt among a few, as they are odious now among all men; neither were ſo read, and vſed earſt, as they are at this time both out of ſight, and out of requeſt, yea and out of mind, and gon, as if they neuer had beene either deuiſed, or vſed in former dayes. And ſo we doubt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15022:17"/>not ſhall happen to the writings of <hi>H. N.</hi> though toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they world ſeeme neuer ſo great a volume, &amp; in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall be verie many.</p>
               <p>Againe, they here commend not their <hi>H. N.</hi> only for his paines, and bringing forth ſuch a volume of theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſpeculations: but alſo for the manner of his writings. <hi>For he neither tooke part with</hi> (ſay they) <hi>nor writ againſt any particular partie, or companie whatſoeuer, as naming them by their names: nor yet praiſed or diſpraiſed any of them by name:</hi> as if to take part, or write againſt any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular partie, or ocmpanie of Heretikes, Schiſmatikes, or other vngodly perſons, and eſpecially in confuting, to name them, were an hainous fault.</p>
               <p>Little thinke theſe Familiars by thus, and this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their <hi>H. N.</hi> whom they touch as faultie, that haue both taken part in a world of diſſentions, ſet themſelues againſt Sectaries; and in their writings, as to all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties eternally horrible, named the authors, and ſpreaders abroad of helliſh errors, by their proper names. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt oppoſed himſelfe profeſſedly againſt the <hi>Phariſies</hi> and <hi>Sadduces;</hi> ſo did the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> againſt the highe Prieſtes and Rulers of <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> ſo <hi>Paule</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Alexander, Demas, Hymeneus, Philetus</hi> and ſuch like; ſo the Euangeliſt <hi>Iohn</hi> againſt the <hi>Nicolaitans;</hi> and ſo the true againſt the falſe Apoſtles, Miniſters and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked perſons from time to time in all ages, whoſe both er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors they haue oppugned, and regiſtred their names for an euerlaſting remembrance.</p>
               <p>And though this <hi>H. H.</hi> neither tooke part with, nor writ againſt any particular partie or company whatſoeuer (which ye is vntrue, as afterward ſhal be ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen) <hi>as naming them by their names</hi> (a thing which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15022:18"/>lawfully, and after the example euen of the beſt, hee might haue done): yet (which hee cannot iuſtifie, nor aunſwere before God) hee oppoſeth himſelfe general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt all men, which bee not of his fect<note n="(a)" place="margin">H.N. 1. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor. c.</hi> 16, §. 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>: whence it is that all men, eſpecially the true Church and ſeruantes of God, are againſt him, and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie.</p>
               <p>Againe, theſe Familiſts (ſtill ouer familiar with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie) would beare his Highneſſe in hand, that the ſaid <hi>H.N.</hi> in his writings doth neither praiſe nor diſpraiſe any partie or companie by name: which is moſt vntrue. For hee commendeth the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and officers thereof; tearming it: <hi>The Communion of all Chriſtians; the Pope, the chiefe annointed; the moſt holy Father; the Cardinalls, moſt holy, and famous, and next the moſt auncienteſt, and holy Father, the Pope in moſt holy Religion, and vnderſtanding</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Euang. cap.</hi> 31. §. 1.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>: and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecieth of an entire, and perfect reſtauration of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall <hi>Hierarchie</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Ibid. §. 23.</note>.</p>
               <p>And on the other ſide, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demneth as many as out of the knowledge which they tooke out of the Scriptures (as all the proteſtant and reformed Churches through-out the world haue done) <hi>brought in certaine ſeruices, and ceremonies in any other wiſe, or order than the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>Appointed</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 32. § 4</note>.</p>
               <p>He raileth on Gods Preachers; and calleth them <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>illuminated, vnregenerated, vnrenewed, vngodded, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> and I wot not what beſides<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 4. §. 4</note>, to bringe their perſons, miniſterie, and profeſſion into vtter hatred and contempt<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 28. §. 4. <hi>Document. ſent. c.</hi> 2. §. 2.</note>.</p>
               <p>And though in his writinges, he had neither ſo prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as he hath done, the Pope and his partakers on the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15022:18"/>one ſide; nor diſpraiſed, and to the pit of hell condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all Miniſters and Preachers (whom in ſcorne euerie where hee tearmeth <hi>Scripture-learned</hi>):<note place="margin">1. <hi>Exhort. c.</hi> 15. §. 17.19.</note>): yet that maketh him not a commendable writer and regardable. For he is aprayſer, and magnifier of himſelfe euerie where in his writings which is the greateſt fault that can be in a man, whether hee write, or ſpeake; and bee his praiſes either true, or falſe; but elſpecially if they be proudly arrogated, and not deſeruedly.</p>
               <p>Would you heare a vaunting Bragadine? Liſten then vnto <hi>H. N.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord, the God of Heauen moued Me in his Minde or Spirit</hi> (ſaith <hi>H. N.</hi>) <hi>his power incompaſſed Mee, with a Ruſhing noyſe:and the glorie of the ſame God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen became great in my ſpirite of his Loue, in ſuch wiſe, that the great cleareneſſe of God wholly innironed Mee, and ſhoane round about Mee, where-through the ſight of mine Eies became clearer than Chryſtall, and mine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding brighter than the Sunne</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>H. N.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: of the Spir. c. <hi>1. §. 2.</hi>
                  </note>; <hi>the Lorde his Being and Eſſence ſpake vnto Mee: for the Being of God gaue-forth his ſound and voice; and ſpake vnto Mee, H. N. through his ſpirit of Loue, all theſe wordes, and ſaide &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 5.</note>. Here the Eſſence and Being of God ſpake vnto him.</p>
               <p>Againe, <hi>I lament</hi>(ſaith <hi>H. N.</hi>) <hi>and bewaile verie much your vnfaithfulneſſe, and all your fainedneſſe, wherewith yee thinke to couer you, before Mee, yet are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe all the Counſailes and falſhoodes of your Harts manifeſted before Me, &amp; ſo much the more naked &amp; bare before the Eies of my Hart, and Spirit</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 3. §. 1.2.3.</note>. Here hee brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth that the Counſailes, &amp; ſecrets of mans hart (knowen onely vnto God) are not hidden from him.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:15022:19"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Many</hi> (ſaith <hi>H. N.</hi>) <hi>could much rather iudge</hi> Moſes, <hi>the Prophets of God, together with the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and God his elected Miniſter</hi> H. N. <hi>to erre or miſſe the right, than that they would by any meanes confeſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that they in the Imagination of their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, concerninge the godly matters, are ignorant, and lying</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Ibid. c. 13. §. 8.</note>.</p>
               <p>Hee vaunteth here that hee could no more erre, than could the Prophets and Apoſtles; yea he preferreth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if his wordes be well obſerued, before the Apoſtles and Prophets.</p>
               <p>In his <hi>Prouerbes: The God of Heauen</hi> (ſaith, <hi>H.N.</hi>)<note n="(k)" place="margin">Chap. 8. §. 3</note> 
                  <hi>as the Father himſelfe, is come downe, and He brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, in the Seruice of his Loue, Himſelfe, with his Chriſt, and Holy Ghoſt, and with all that which with Him is Gods, vnto his obedient Man:</hi> H. N. <hi>And Godding the ſame with Him, He hath manned him with the ſame: and his will is, that nowe in the laſt time, through the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Loue, all people or generations of Men, which are good-Willing to his Righteouſneſſe, ſhould aſſemble them vnto Him, and his godded Man; and euen ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with them, all that is manly; To the ende that they all ſhould become of one Being with him, and his Godded man: and ſo bee all named Gods and Children of the moſt-higheſt.</hi> Here is hee deified, and made a God. Is this fellowe, and his writings to bee commended, and that vnto a moſt religious King: or not rather to bee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred, and all that praiſe him, both of Prince and people?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15022:19"/>
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>BVt doth<note n="*" place="margin">The conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts H. N. his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</note> onely ſhewe in particular in his ſayd wrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings (as ſayth he, the vnpartiall Seruice of Loue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth) what is good or euill for euery one, and wherein the man hath right or wrong in any point, whether it be in the ſtate of his ſoule towards God,<note place="margin">Moſt falſe. <hi>Vide reſponſum.</hi>
                  </note> or in the ſtate of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy towardes the Magiſtrates of the world, and towardes one another.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AS earſt for the manner: ſo heere haue we</hi> H. N. <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled for the doctrine, and matter by him deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But as afore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt the doctrine of H. N.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpeaking to the purpoſe which heere they do, they ſay</hi> the ſeruice &amp; writings of <hi>H. N.</hi> taught them all dutiful obedience towards God, &amp; Magiſtrates &amp;c. <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing therin with the</hi> holy Scriptures as they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>that is in that ſenſe, and meaning, &amp; none otherwiſe, which they giue of the Scriptures: ſo in this place they ſay of</hi> H. N. <hi>that hee doth onely</hi> ſhew in generall in his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, what is good or euill for euery one, and wherein the man hath right or wrong in any point &amp;c. <hi>but it is not as the holy Scripture (in the natiue ſenſe thereof, without the</hi> Families <hi>partiall interpretations and gloſſes) but as the vnpartiall (than which nothing is more partiall)</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Loue, <hi>requireth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee cannot therefore well vnderſtand, what is the godlineſſe and iuſtice, which</hi> H. N. <hi>in his writings dooth promote, vnleſſe we firſt know, what this their</hi> Seruice of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15022:20"/>Loue, <hi>heere mentioned, is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The vnpartial</hi> Seruice of Loue <hi>in this place mentioned is the religion, principles, and ſpirituall exerciſes of</hi> H. N. <hi>or his illuminate Elders, in the</hi> Family of Loue. <hi>For the right conceiuing whereof we are to obſerue how ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to</hi> H. N. <hi>his doctrine, there be eight thorough-breakings</hi> (<hi>which is</hi> H. N. <hi>his word</hi>) <hi>or</hi> Reuelations <hi>of Goods true light vnto mankindes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">H.N. Prouerbs Ch. §. 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>the firſt was to</hi> Adam, <hi>&amp; held till</hi> Noe; <hi>the ſecond from</hi> Noe <hi>till</hi> Abraham, <hi>the third from</hi> Abraham <hi>till</hi> Moſes; <hi>the fourth from</hi> Moſes <hi>till</hi> Samuel, Dauid, <hi>and</hi> Salomon; <hi>the firſt form them till</hi> Zorobabel; <hi>the ſixt from</hi> Zorobabel <hi>till CHRIST; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth from CHRIST till</hi> H. N. <hi>in whoſe dayes the Lord,</hi> out of his mercifull loue, raiſed vp the gracious word, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſes, and elected H. N. thereto <hi>(if you will beliue him)</hi> for to miniſter the ſame vnder the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his loue, to the erecting or reſtoring of his true sanctuarie, and of the true offering, and God ſeruice in the ſame.</p>
               <p>Through which gracious word &amp; <hi>H. N. God</hi> reuealed <hi>(ſayth H. N.)</hi> the appearing of the comming of his Chriſt, and the newe day of his righteous iudgement,<note place="margin">☞</note> as alſo the Flowing forth of his holy Spirit of loue, to the awaking &amp; Riſing vp of all his Holy-ones, out of the ſleep to the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lordlineſſe with Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; to an euerlaſting faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding kingdome of the godly Maieſtie, vpon the ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, according to his promiſes.</p>
               <p>Euen thus hath God declared (<hi>ſayth</hi> H. N.) with H. N. the eight thorough-breaking of his true light, vpon the earth, wheein the Lord, the God of Heauen, reſtored the former kingdome with his garniſhing, together with all that which God hath ſpoken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the world
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15022:20"/>through the mouth of his holy Prophets,<note place="margin">☜</note> and of the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes of his Chriſt: and the ſame eight thorough-breaking of the true light of God vpon the earth, is the newe day; to therenewing of the life, which God hath tofore appointed to reueile the ſame in the laſt time, for to iudge in the ſame the vniuerſall Earth with righteouſneſſe, to the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all the enimies of God and Chriſt, together with all the enemies of the godly life, and blaſphemers of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, and ſeruice of Loue; and to the erecting of his vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Sanctuarie, the ſeat of his Maieſtie, and the vpright gouernment of his holy ones, vnder the obedience of his loue, vpon the earth, and alſo for to declare euen ſo vpon the earth, in the ſame true light of the newe or eight day, the myſteries of God and Chriſt, euen from the beginning of the world, till vnto the end. <hi>All theſe bee the verie words of</hi> H. N. <hi>touching his myſteries</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 16.17.18.</note>: the reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>whereof by him vnto the elders, and by them vnto the yong ones in the</hi> Family, <hi>is by him called</hi> The ſeruice or miniſtration of the Loue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of which light and ſeruice, wonderfull things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued by the <hi>Family:</hi> I will onely cite a place, ſhewing their conceipt of the ſeruice here mentioned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I foretell you aſſuredly (<hi>ſayth</hi> Fidelitas) that the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the wicked world (haue therefore a circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect conſideration hereon, O ye children of men) ſhall break in among you, and ye ſhall likewiſe be vehemently aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therewith. Neuertheleſſe if you holde you firmely to the requiring of the gracious word, and his Seruice of Loue: ye ſhall then be deliuered from the wicked aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings which come againſt you, out of the Abhominations of the wicked world, and out of the falſehood of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſters, and inherit the Crowne of the eternall life, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15022:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>the true anointing of the ioifull oyle of the holy Spirit of the Loue of Ieſu Chriſt: and euen ſo find by experience that our God of Loue is the true God; and that we his obedient Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munaltie of the Loue, are his acceptable people, and that they alſo which bide eſtranged from the ſame God, as alſo remaine without vs and our Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munaltie, and without the requiring of the gracious word and his Serurce of Loue, or withdraw themſelues therefrom, haue no liuing God, nor yet true God ſeruice: but are without God, and without God ſeruice in this world. For our God of Loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the true liuing God, and beſides him there is no God more, and his God ſeruice of Loue, which we miniſter, vnder the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his Loue; is the true ſafe-making God ſeruice, and beſides the ſame there is not any God ſeruice more, neither in heauen nor yet in earth, <hi>Hitherto</hi> Fidelitas<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Distinct. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar</hi> §. 1 c. 11.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From which place of</hi> H. N. <hi>and</hi> Fidelitas, <hi>note, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader, that their words vnto his Mareſtie</hi> viz. that the writings of <hi>H. N.</hi> or ſeruice of Loue, further true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and godlineſſe, <hi>are moſt falſe, and vttered either by ſome ignorants which know not what the</hi> Seruice of Loue <hi>meaneth; or of policie to bleare his Highneſſe eyes, that hee ſhould not perceaue the daunger of this pretended</hi> Loue Seruice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerue, next, their opinion of this their</hi> Seruice of Loue, <hi>as that</hi> it is the true ſafe-making Gods ſeruice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides which there is not any God ſeruice more, neither in heauen, nor yet in earth; and that whoſo haue not this ſeruice, or withdraw themſelues therefrom, haue no liuing God: <hi>and hence coniecture what their thoughts be, not onely of the</hi> Seruice <hi>of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtian Churches, but of the doctrine alſo in them profeſſed, with all profeſſors of Chriſtianitie, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15022:21"/>and Aduerſaries to</hi> H. N. <hi>and his newe</hi> Seruice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beſides, it is not to be neglected, that the doctrine in the</hi> Seruice of Loue <hi>deliuered, by</hi> H. N. <hi>in theſe places is called,</hi> The newe day: The day of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Reſurrection: The day of iudgement, of the ſecond comming of Chriſt; of the reſtoring of all things: of the fulfilling of all that which God hath ſpoken from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world through the mouth of his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and the Euangeliſts of his Chriſt. <hi>All which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrate</hi> H. N. <hi>his doctrine touching the generall reſurrection; the day of iudgement: the ſecond comming of Chriſt: euerlaſting life; and finally the accompliſhing of GODS promiſes, made vnto the Patriarches, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Church from euerlaſting (encluded in the writings of</hi> H.N. <hi>and ſo in the</hi> Seruice of Loue) <hi>to be moſt hereticall and damnable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This conſidered, impudent, and ſhameleſſe are theſe</hi> Familiſtes, <hi>that woulde beare the moſt religious Prince in hand, that the writings of</hi> H. N. <hi>and</hi> Seruice of Loue, <hi>make for the aduancement of godlineſſe, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie: when rightly examined, it ouerthroweth the very groundes and principles of true Religion, without which there can bee no ſounde practiſe of honeſtie and iuſtice among men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>TO the end that all people (when they heare, or read his writinges, and doe thereby perceaue their ſinnes,<note place="margin">The end of his writings.</note> and eſtranging from GOD, and Chriſt, mought ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour them to bring forth the due fruictes of Repentance,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15022:22"/>which is reformation, and neweneſſe of life, according as all the holy Scriptures doe likewiſe require the ſame of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one; and that they mought in that ſort, become ſaued through Ieſus <hi>CHRIST,</hi> the onely Sauiour of all the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEere reade wee the ende indeede of</hi> H. N. <hi>his wrightings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt the end of H. N. his wrightings.</note> viz. to inuite all men vnto repentance, and neweneſſe of life: <hi>and yet deſerueth hee no praiſe at all</hi> (<hi>as the</hi> Familistes <hi>woulde make his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe belieue hee dooth) for this exhortation of his. For what meaneth hee by Repentance, but that all men, not yet of his Family, ſhould forſake or abiure the Religion, which they haue beene brought vp in, and vnlearne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine whatſoeuer they haue taken on, and learned to themſelues, out of the Scriptures, in the Chriſtian aſſemblies, where GODS word is read, preached, and hearde? VVhat by neweneſſe of life? But that wee become young ones in the</hi> Family, <hi>or houſe of</hi> Loue? <hi>VVhat by ſaluation? but the ſtate of a</hi> Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list; <hi>which is all pure; or of an</hi> Elder <hi>in the louely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All people (<hi>ſayth</hi> H. N.) are called, and friendly bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, through <hi>H. N.</hi> to the repentance for their ſinnes, and to the houſe of the loue of Ieſus Chriſt; the Rest of all the Saints or children of God;<note n="(a)" place="margin">H.N. Cri voice c. 1. §. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let euery one leaue now his owne word, doctrine, and taken on knowledge, and alſo the word, the doctrine, and knowledge of al vnſent Preachers, and good-thinking wiſe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15022:22"/>where-through yee are ſeduced &amp;c. and come now all to this ſame Sanctuarie of GOD<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> c. 2. §. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>meaning</hi> the houſe of Loue, <hi>called before,</hi> the Reſt of all the Saints or children of God.</p>
               <p>Come alſo now all, which, through your ignorant know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or miſunderſtanding, haue withdrawen your ſelues (<hi>ſayth</hi> H. N.) from this ſame ſtoole of grace, and louely houſe of the Loue of Ieſu Chriſt; and, from our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munalty, taken occaſion of offence at our littleneſſe or ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenes, &amp; at the godly Teſtimonies of our ſayings; and euen ſo made vp your ſelues, as Reſiſters, againſt vs, and our good doctrine, and exerciſes, or orders, ſeparated your ſelues from vs, and growen to be bitter minded or diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed toward vs, together with all yee that haue miſtruſted vs, alſo not belieued the holy word of the eternall truth, which, we through Gods grace, adminiſter vnder the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Loue, but doubted therof &amp;c. and repent you of your ſinnes, to your ſanctification, and to the health of your ſoules<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 7.</note>.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide (<hi>ſaith</hi> H. N.), All thoſe which loue rather the darknes, that the Light; cleaue more vnto the world, and the worldly thinges, than vnto the gracious Worde in the <hi>Seruice of Loue;</hi> heare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, and followe rather their good thinking, than the Testimonies of the holy <hi>Spirit of Loue,</hi> which are ſet forth and offered vnto them, by the Elders in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communaltie of Loue, out of the heauenly truth; and euen ſo waxe offended thereat, or hold them backe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, and reſiſt the <hi>Seruice of Loue,</hi> Thoſe ſhall all, if they turne them not to the <hi>Seruice of the Loue,</hi> nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent them of their ſinnes, become broken in pieces, and iuſtly beare their blame, or be puniſhed, with the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15022:23"/>deſtruction, and bide captiued, for euer and euer, with the death and mortalitie<note n="(d)" place="margin">H. N. <hi>Exhort.</hi> c. 14. §. 10.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnto this</hi> Repentance <hi>doth</hi> H. N. <hi>exhort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is the opinion, which</hi> H. N. <hi>had, and his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and ſchollers haue of themſelues, and their fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; they are all forſooth in the ſtate of ſaluation, and cannot periſh: but they who neither bee</hi> Familiſtes, <hi>nor wel-willers to their doctrine, exerciſes and orders, are all vnder the curſe of God, like eternally to bee damned, vnleſſe they alter their mindes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their faith and religion (thoughe grounded vppon the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles), becauſe with</hi> H. N. <hi>the</hi> Diuell is their Father<note n="(e)" place="margin">Spirit. Land <hi>preſ.</hi> §. 9.</note>, and they are the children of wrath, a curſed people coheires of the euerlasting fire<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 10.</note>, and ſhall bee caſt into the bottom-leſſe pit, into the fire of Hell<note n="(g)" place="margin">H. N. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs. <hi>c.</hi> 5. §. 15.</note>: <hi>Then which concluſions nothing is more Hereticall, and accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and this was it, among other thinges, why his Maieſtie tearmed theſe</hi> Familiſtes, Puritanes, <hi>and</hi> a moſt vile Secte, viz. <hi>euen becauſe</hi> they deeme all the world beſides themſelues, to bee but abhomination in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their</hi> H. N. <hi>ſpeaketh much of Ieſus Chriſt in his bookes: but in no one place that I coulde yet meete withall, dooth hee acknowledge Chriſt to bee eyther true GOD, or very man, at leaſt not GOD and man in one perſon; but commonly with him hee is an allegoricall CHRIST, meant either by the Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth day, which the Lord commaunded to be alwayes had in remembrance</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">H. N. <hi>Enang. cap.</hi> 13. §. 2. 2 <hi>Document-ſent. c.</hi> 3. §. 4.</note>; <hi>or by the Seruice or doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of</hi> H. N. <hi>which alſo is CHRIST after the fleſh</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exhort.</hi> c. 14. §. 1.</note>, <hi>as hee vnderſtandeth the Scriptures; or by the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15022:23"/>vertuous qualities, and Being in godly men</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Enang. c.</hi> 13. §. 16. 1. <hi>Exhort. c.</hi> 1 §. 24.25. <hi>ca.</hi> 20. §. 5.</note>; <hi>or by the oldeſt</hi> Elder <hi>in the</hi> Familie, <hi>which ſometimes was</hi> H. N. <hi>and is now one man, now another.</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Euang. c.</hi> 31. §. 12.14.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>An obedient, and godly life, is Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>ſaith the</hi> Exile<note n="(m)" place="margin">Patterne of preſ. Temps.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo are men ſaued, by the doctrine of this Familie, either by their owne workes or vertues; or by their Ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Elders; or by the doctrine of H: N:</hi> or Seruice of Loue, <hi>or by the holie</hi> Reſt; <hi>but neuer by our Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged in the Church of</hi> England.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue yee the ende of</hi> H. N. <hi>his writinges; ſuitable certes vnto his method and doctrine, for which he is ſo renowned (but to their ſmall comfort, and credit) among the</hi> Familiſtes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding, deare Soueraigne, yet hath the ſaid Author, and his doctrine a lone time, and ſtillis,<note place="margin">The Families complaint.</note> moſt ſhamefully, and falſely ſlandered, by our foreſaide aduerſaries both in this Land, and in diuers others, as to be repleniſhed with all manner of damnable errors, and filthie libertie of the fleſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>AFter a long, and lothſome narration, they come now to a new complaint, and that ſtill on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of their <hi>H. N.</hi> and his diſciples.</p>
               <p>It is not yet an hundred yeares, ſince the ſaid author was borne; nor 60. yeares ſince his doctrine came firſt to light, and was broched; nor 50. yeares yet, ſince it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15022:24"/>in this realme (a bleſſed thing had it beene for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a Chriſtian ſoule, had either <hi>H. N.</hi> neuer breathed, or his doctrine neuer beene hatched).</p>
               <p>But how many yeares ſoeuer haue paſſed ſince his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and myſteries came to light (if hitherto they bee all knowen); through the goodneſſe of God yet, there is not one, of al the Churches Proteſtant, and reformed, that fauoureth, but all bid open and vtter defiance to <hi>H. N.</hi> his bookes, and errors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>H. N.</hi> himſelfe in his life time much complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that all degrees in all Lands abhorred his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings<note n="(a)" place="margin">H.N. 1. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frein.</hi> §. 4.</note>.</p>
               <p>In this Land both <hi>H.N.</hi> and his lothſome (which he calleth <hi>Louely</hi>) <hi>Familie of Loue,</hi> haue beene diſplaied once, confuted often, reſiſted alwayes: but ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and falſely ſlandered, either by forraine, or home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writers, it was neuer that hetherto I could heare; and ſo muſt I thinke, till I ſee the extant writings againſt them, conuicted of vntruthes, and diſproued as ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous.</p>
               <p>That <hi>H.N.</hi> his bookes are repleniſhed with dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable errors, it will be iuſtified; and hath alreadie in this examination, and elſe where beene manifeſted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>AND wee his wel-willers, and fauourers, in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right drift of his doctrine (as aforeſaid) haue alſo been by them complained on, and accuſed vnto our late gracious Soueraigne, &amp; the Magiſtrates of this Land, both long time paſt, and nowe lately againe, as to bee a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo infected, and ſtained with all manner of deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15022:24"/>wickedneſſe, and errors, that are not worthie to liue vpon the earth (but yet would neuer preſent any of his bookes vnto his Maieſtie to peruſe, nor yet ſet them forth in any indifferent, or true manner to the viewe of the world; leaſt their malitious and ſlanderous reportes and accuſations againſt the ſame, and vs, ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by haue beene reuealed, and diſproued to their great ſhame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examniation.</head>
               <p>NOw complaine they of iniuries offered to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               <p>The verie drift of <hi>H.N.</hi> is to thwart, or diſcredit ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatſoeuer is taught in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and elſe-where, from the letter of the holy Scriptures; and to bring in another Goſpell, <hi>viz.</hi> after <hi>H. N.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such as are the wil-willers and fauourers of <hi>H.N.</hi> in the ſaid his drift (as the <hi>Familiſts</hi> here confeſſe themſelues to be) not only deſerue to bee complained vppon, and accuſed vnto authoritie, but to bee accurſed of God and man (if they perſiſt in their wicked courſe) as a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple infected with moſt deteſtable wickedneſſe, and errors; and the verie plague, and bane of ſound religion. And thoſe men which haue acquainted authoritie with their errors, and impieties, haue done good ſeruice therin, and their bounden duties, both vnto God, his Church, and the State.</p>
               <p>Whether any of <hi>H. H.</hi> his bookes haue beene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto our late moſt gratious Soueraigne (of aie bleſſed memorie) I cannot ſay; but I ſurely coniecture, that ſhee could not be ignorant of the contents of his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15022:25"/>writinges: when the Lords of her Counſaile (as afore hath beene declared) cenſured ſome of her houſe-hold ſeruants for abbetting <hi>H. N.</hi> and his deteſtable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</p>
               <p>They which againe doe ſay that their aduerſaries would neuer preſent any of <hi>H. N.</hi> his bookes vnto her Maieſtie to peruſe, ſay more then they can affirme, yea which is palpably vntrue. For, who abhorreth <hi>H. N.</hi> &amp; his bookes or <hi>H.N.</hi> rather for his hereticall blaſphemies, but euer were deſirous that his ſaid errors, contained in his books, might in his ſaid bookes be read of her Maieſtie; that by her authoritie the better they, and al ſuch as fauour thoſe bookes, containing ſuch errors, might condignely be cenſured?</p>
               <p>When theſe <hi>Familiſtes</hi> dare tell his Maieſtie, that their aduerſaries would neuer preſent <hi>H. N.</hi> his bookes, nor any of them vnto her Highneſſe, it appeareth (they herein ſaying true) that ſhe had alwayes about her ſome <hi>Familiſtes,</hi> or fauourers of that Sect, who alwaies related, or bare tidinges what was donne, or intended againſt them.</p>
               <p>It is wiſhed, that his nowe Maieſties Court were purged from ſuch well willers and fauourers of <hi>H. N.</hi> in the maine drift of his helliſh, &amp; hereticall doctrine, where-with her Maieſties was but too-much reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
               <p>How <hi>H. N.</hi> his bookes by their aduerſaries, haue beene ſet-forth, the worlde may iudge. 26. yeares haue they beene extant: a ſufficient time for the <hi>Familie</hi> both to iuſtifie their <hi>H. N.</hi> and to diſcouer the malice &amp; ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous reports of their accuſers, if there were iuſt cauſe. Hitherto haue the Familiſtes beene ſilent, and yet are
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15022:25"/>both confident in their wicked courſes; &amp; not aſhamed to expreſſe ſo much before his moſt-Chriſtian, and roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Maieſtie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>THrough which their moſt-odious &amp; falſe complaints againſt vs, the Magiſtrates did then,<note place="margin">A new and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous narration.</note> and alſo haue now lately caſt diuers of vs into priſon, to our great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance, and diſcredite: but yet haue neuer proued againſt vs, by ſufficient and true teſtimonie, any one of their many foule accuſations (as the records in ſuch caſes and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates that haue dealt therein can teſtific) but are ſo vtterly voide of due, and lawfull proofe thereof, that they haue framed diuers ſubtle Articles for vs (being plaine, and vnlearned men) to aunſwere vpon our oath, whereby to vrge, and gather ſome things from our ſelues, ſo to approue their falſe, and vnchriſtian accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be true, or elſe will force vs to renounce, recant, and condemne that which wee doe not wilfullie maintaine, nor iuſtifie (much like as it was practiced in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, againſt the Chriſtians): yea they are not aſhamed to laie their owne, and all other mens diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and wicked actes (of what profeſſion ſoeuer they be) vpon our backes, to the ende cunningly to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe fauour, and credite to themſelues, and to make vs ſeeme monſtrous &amp; deteſtable before the Magiſtrates, and the common people euerie where; for that wee, and the doctrine of <hi>H. N.</hi> mought (without any indifferent triall, and lawfull, or orderly proceeding, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath beene vſed in the Chriſtian Church in ſuch caſes, for confutinge and condemning of hereſies)
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15022:26"/>be vtterly rooted out of the Land: with diuers other moſt cruell practices, proceeding out of thei bitter and enuious hartes toward vs, tending to the ſame vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and mercileſſe purpoſe, the which wee will here o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to ſpeake of, becauſe wee haue alreadie beene ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedious vnto your Highneſſe; moſt humblie crauing your moſt gratious pardon, and patience therein, in reſpect that wee ſpeake to cleare our ſelues of ſuch matter as may touch our liues and liberties (which are two of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt iewels that GOD hath giuen to mankinde in this world) and alſo for that we haue fewe friendes, or anie other meanes then this to acquaint your Highneſſe with the truth, and ſtate of our cauſe (whereof we thinke your Maieſtie is altogether ignorant) but haue verie many eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies whom we doe greatly ſuſpect will not be ſlacke to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute their falſe, and malitious purpoſe againſt vs vnto your Highneſſe, euen like as they haue accuſtomed to doe in times paſt vnto our late Soueraigne Queene: through which preuailing in thier ſlanderous defacing of us, &amp; our cauſe, diuers of vs (for want of friendes to make it right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowen vnto her Maieſtie) haue ſundrie times been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to endure their iniurious dealinges toward vs, to our great vexation, and hinderance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>HEre haue wee an intricate, and long perplexed pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod deuoide of charitie, diſcretion, and truth; but full of gaule, odious compariſons, and vniuſt complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; and that not only of priuate perſons, their accuſers whoſoeuer, but euen of publike Magiſtrates, &amp; their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, firſt and laſt, againſt this <hi>Familie,</hi> and all for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15022:26"/>their fauouring and wel-wiſhing to <hi>H. N.</hi> and his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: which becauſe it is fitter for the ſaid Magiſtrates, her odiouſly traduced, to cenſure, and aunſwere (whoſe doings againſt the <hi>Familiſts</hi> I am ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of, and yet am perſwaded haue alwaies beene both mild towards them and iuſt) I omitte, and commend the further conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this their hainous complaint vnto the ſupreme authoritie, and his Aſſiſtants, and delegats.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>WHerefore, moſt gratious Soueraigne this is nowe,<note place="margin">Their 1. Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> our humble ſuite vnto your Highneſſe, that when your Kingly affaires of importance, which your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie hath nowe in hand ſhall bee well ouer-paſt, and finiſhed (for the proſperous performance wherof, we will, as dutie bindeth vs, daiely pray vnto Almightie God) that then your Highneſſe will be pleaſed (becauſe we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies taken the ſame authors worke aforeſaid to proceed out of the great grace, and loue of God, and Chriſtes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended towards all Kings, Princes, Rulers, and people vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the vniuerſall earth (as hee himſelfe in many of his workes doth witneſſe no leſſe) to their ſaluation, vnitie, peace, and concord in the ſame godly Loue) to grant vs that fauour, at your Maieſties fitte, and conuenient time, to peruſe the bookes your ſelf, with an vnpartial eie, conferring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the holy Scriptures, wherein it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the bookes that are ſet-foorth vnder your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe name that you haue had great trauaile, and are therefore the better able to iudge betwixt trueth and falſehoode: and wee will whenſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe your Highneſſe to appoint the time, and to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15022:27"/>command, and licence vs thereto) doe our beſt indeuour to procure ſo many of the bookes as we can out of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> (where they bee printed) to bee deliuered vnto your Maieſtie, or ſuch godly learned, and indifferent men, as it ſhall pleaſe your Maieſtie to appoint.</p>
               <p>And wee will alſo (vnder your Highneſſe lawfull licence, and commaundement in that behalfe) doe our like indeuour to procure ſome of the learned men of that Countrie (if there bee any yet remaininge aliue, that were well acquainted with the author and his workes in his life time, and which likewiſe haue exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his workes euer ſince) to come ouer, and attend vpon your Maieſtie, at your appointed time conuenient, who can much more ſufficiently inſtruct, and reſolue your Highneſſe in anie vnuſuall wordes, phraze, or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that may happilie ſeeme darke, and doubtfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Maieſtie, than any of vs in this your land are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>NOwe are wee come, at the length, vnto their Petition. The grounde whereof is a deepe, and heauenly conceipt which they haue of their <hi>H. N.</hi> and the worke by him vndertaken, for the ſaluation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <p>Many are <hi>H.N.</hi> his prophecies of his good ſucceſſe and future preuailing through out the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This ſame kingdome of peace, and of Loue</hi> (ſaith the ſaid <hi>H. N.</hi> ſpeaking of this <hi>Familie</hi>) <hi>ſhall, through the adminiſtration of the gratious word of the Lord, ſpread abroad and bid all people, to their preſeruation, therunto;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15022:27"/>to the intent that all Kingdomes of the world ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble them to this one Kingdome of peace and of Loue, and that &amp;c. to the ioy and ſaluation of all the children of men</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">H. N. 1. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort. c. 12. §. 40.</note>.</p>
               <p>Againe: <hi>This ſame God ſeruice, this loue and louely being, and the ſound or fame of the ſame ſhall breake in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all nations of people, and let it ſelfe to be heard ouer all lands</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ibid. c. 14. § 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Of all Prouinces, the firſt that receiued the Chriſtian faith by publike allowance, was <hi>Britany</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Sabel. Aenei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad. 7. lib. 5.</note>. The firſt king chriſtened, that we read of was <hi>Lucius</hi> K. of <hi>Britanie.</hi> And among Kings chriſtened, if not the firſt, yet with the firſt, hee that expelled the Pope, and his courtes, was <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>viij;</hi> and that rooted out all his deteſtable enormities out of his dominions, was <hi>Edward the vi.</hi> Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Oh what a cordiall ioy, and comfort would it be vnto this <hi>Family,</hi> that of all Prouinces, which ſhall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour their <hi>Loue Seruice, Britanie</hi> would be the firſt, and to the glorie of his noble aunceſtors, that it might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, how our moſt illuſtrious King IAMES was the firſt that ſupplanted the Scripture learning (brought in by King <hi>Lucius,</hi> and reeſtabliſhed by great <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> laſt mentioned) for the implanting of the <hi>Seruice of Loue,</hi> and <hi>H. N.</hi> his illuſions, I ſhould ſay illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions! which that all Kings one day will implant, they haue no doubt; &amp; that our King IAMES may of al be the firſt, is their heartie deſire, &amp; end of their inſtant perition.</p>
               <p>Hence they humbly beſeech his Maieſtie to peruſe the bookes of their <hi>H. N,</hi> himſelfe, with an vnpartiall eye, as the principall meanes to make him a <hi>Familiſt,</hi> and a Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of that houſehold of <hi>Loue,</hi> eſpecially within his owne Realmes, and Dominions: which he vouchſafing to do,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15022:28"/>they promiſe by their beſt endeuour to procure his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty ſo many of <hi>H. N.</hi> his bookes, as they can; and of ſuch their illuminats, as they can heare of, euer inward with <hi>H. N.</hi> &amp; his doctrine, &amp; well exerciſed in his works, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in his tongue, words &amp; phraſes, and all out of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> Which is a bold offer of theirs; and the more audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and graceleſſe, becauſe they confeſſe here his Ma. to be Scripture-learned, &amp; we know him among Chriſtian Princes, the chiefeſt Patrone of all men ſtudious, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant in the Scriptures of God (which kind of men, of all others, theſe <hi>Familiſtes</hi> (cannot brook): which Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Scripture-learned men, are moſt oppoſite, &amp; euer haue beene, to <hi>H. N.</hi> his doctrine; and his doctrine, <hi>Seruice of Loue</hi> or ſecrets contrarie, nothing more, vnto the ſayd Scriptures, and ſuch learned men. <hi>For</hi> ſayth <hi>H. N.</hi> (as hath afore beene alleadged, and is neuer by mee mentioned, but in deteſtation of the ſpeech:) <hi>It is aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly all falſe and lyes, ſeducing, and deceitfull, that the vngodded, or vnilluminated Men, out of the imagination or riches of their owne knowledge, and of their learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Scriptures, bring foorth, inſtitute, preach, and teach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, what a mockery is it, to beare his Highneſſe in hand, that <hi>H. N.</hi> his workes and wrightings, rightly, and with an vnpartiall eye conſidered, are nothing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant from the Scriptures of God? knowing (vnleſſe they credit him not herein) their oldeſt Elder, and chiefeſt <hi>Illuminate,</hi> H. N. vtterly, as falſe, and lyes, ſeducing and deceitfull, to condemne whatſoeuer is grounded vpon the ſame Scriptures of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:15022:28"/>
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>ANd ſo vpon ſuch your Highneſſe godly, aduiſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation, and cenſure thereupon (finding the ſame workes hereticall, or ſedicious, and not agreeable to Gods holy word, and teſtimonies of all the Scriptures) to leaue them to take them, as your Maieſties lawes ſhall ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in appoint vs; hauing no intent, nor meaning to contend, or reſiſt there-againſt, howſoever it be, but dutifully to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey thereunto, according to the counſell of the Scriptures, and alſo of the ſayd Authors workes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>VPon his Maieſties cenſuring of <hi>H. N.</hi> his doctrine, and vvrightinges, they promiſe obedience vnto his lawes, and proceedinges: which is conſcionably they doe performe, then ſhall they ſhewe themſelues to bee honeſt and good men. But the doctrine of diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and temporizing is ſo often diſperſed, and riſe in <hi>H. N.</hi> his wrightinges; and the ſayde workes of H. N. in all this their ſupplication, ſo magnified; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in this their verie petition, ſo expreſly acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to proceede <hi>euen out of the great grace, and loue of God, and Chriſt, extended towardes all Kings, Princes, Rulers, and people vpon the vniuerſall earth to their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, &amp;c.</hi> as it is to be feared, that what obedience ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d outwardly to his Maieſties lawes, iniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; conſtitutions, their heart yet diſſenteth from his, and all Religions elſe in the world differing from theirs; to which notwithſtanding for quietneſſe ſake, they will
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15022:29"/>not ſticke perhaps outwardly to conforme themſelues, whereſoeuer they reſide, in <hi>Great Britanie,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> to the Kings profeſſion; in <hi>Spaine,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſewhere to the Romane ſuperſtition and idolatry<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pattern of the preſ. Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ps.</note> in externall matters alwayes following the ſtronger part, reſeruing their hearts vnto their <hi>H. N.</hi> and his <hi>Seruice of Loue:</hi> as many Papiſtes doe vnto the Pope, according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction in like caſes, where they are too weake, <hi>Da mihi cor Fili, &amp; ſufficit.</hi> For our <hi>Familiſtes</hi> are Free men, and can walke in all freedome among all people<note n="(b)" place="margin">H. N. Spir. Land. c. 41. § 6.</note>.</p>
               <p>VVhat the religion is which his Maieſtie dooth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and will reſolutely, as Gods holy and onely truth, protect, is well knowne to his Highneſſe Subiectes, yea to the whole World<note n="(c)" place="margin">Proclam. at Wilt. 27. Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tob. At Weſtm. 22. Feb. 5. March. At the parliam. 19. March. 163.</note>. A Religion grounded vpon the Scriptures; aduerſant to all humane inuentions, and ſpirituall, or diabolicall reuelations, and viſions whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. Now put-caſe his Maieſtie will not vouchſafe (as good hope is he will not) from his moſt ſerious &amp; weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affaires of his kingdome, to ſteale opportunitie to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaie the wrightings of <hi>H. N.</hi> yea, will neither reade them himſelfe, nor yet, like <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great<note n="(d)" place="margin">Tripart. hiſt. lib. 2. c. 15.</note>, ſuffer his well meaning Subiectes, of weake capacities, to reade, yea nor to deteine ſuch wrightings by them, as are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, contrary, or differing from the religion by himſelfe profeſſed, by Lawe eſtabliſhed, and which truly embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced will bring men to ſaluation: will not our <hi>Family</hi> giue ouer their <hi>Loue Seruice,</hi> to ſerue God, as the King and his lawfull ſubiectes do, according to Gods word?</p>
               <p>Their wordes before, that they neuer <hi>heard, nor knew any lawe eſtabliſhed in this Realme againſt H. N. and his bookes:</hi> and their ſecret, and parlour meetings, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15022:29"/>of their <hi>H. N.</hi> his <hi>Seruices,</hi> euen from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning almoſt of that bleſſed Queenes raigne (ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH of freſh, and honorable remembrance) doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimate, how it is neither the Kings owne writings, Proclamations, Actes, Statutes, Eccleſiaſticall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and Conſtitutions, nor whatſoeuer elſe hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeth for the ratification of one, and the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (and condemnation of all others, contrarie, or croſſing the ſame) in his Realmes, and Dominions, that they regarde, or will yielde vnto, vntill his Highneſſe, with good diſcretion hath read, and vpon ſound aduiſe, diſallowed and cenſured, as hereticall, ſeditious, or diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant from Gods holy word, the workes, and writings of their <hi>H. N.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For vpon ſuch his Highneſſe godly, aduiſed, &amp; graue conſultation and Cenſures, they promiſe to yielde, and leaue the workes, bookes, and wrightings of their doctor, <hi>H.N.</hi> but not afore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>ANd our further humble ſute vnto your Highneſſe is,<note place="margin">Their ſecond Petition.</note> that of your gracious fauour and clemencie, you will grant, and giue order vnto your Maieſties Officers in that behalf, that all of vs, your faithfull louing Subiects, which are now in priſon in any part of this your Realme for the ſame cauſe, may be releaſed vpon ſuch bayle, or bonde, as we are able to giue; and that neither we, nor any of that company (behauing our ſelues orderly (and obediently vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Highneſſe Lawes) may be any further perſecuted, or troubled therein, vntill ſuch time as your Maiestie, and ſuch godly, learned, and indifferent men of your clergie,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15022:30"/>as your Highneſſe ſhall appoint thereto) ſhall haue aduiſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſuited, and determined of the matter, whereby that we may not be vtterly waſted by the great charge of impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment &amp; perſecution, and by the hard dealing of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries. For we are a people but fewe in number, and yet most of vs very poore in worldly wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>HIs Maieſtie by good aduiſe, and counſell, hath rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Religion of his immediat Predeceſſor, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in 39. Articles, agreed vpon by the whole Clergie of this Realme in a lawful aſſembly or Conuocation, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Anno.</hi> 1562. Hee hath alſo publiſhed his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eccleſ. consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. &amp; can. an. <hi>1604.</hi>
                  </note> how all, and euery his Subiects of <hi>England,</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely ſhall carry themſelues, according to their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all places: If theſe <hi>Familistes</hi> therefore will profeſſe the ſame religion with him, and his truly good Subiectes; if they alſo will frequent orderly the ſacred Aſſemblies and Sacraments; if they will demeane themſelues as it becommeth ſober Chriſtians, and laye aſide all <hi>H. N.</hi> his erroneous and deteſtable writinges; if they will approoue the <hi>Seruice</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and finally forſake their conuenticling, chaire preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, and Seruices, adminiſtred among them by their illuminated, and codeified Elders, they neede feare no perſecution, or trouble: otherwiſe why ſhould they not feare the ſword, when they will not be ordered by the word of God?</p>
               <p>They ſay they are in number but fewe. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they abuſe his Maieſties royall eares and eyes.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:15022:30"/>
               <p> It is well knowen howe twentie fiue yeares agoe the number of them was great, and they diſperſed in diuers partes; as <hi>Surrey; Suſſex; Middleſex, Bark-ſhire; Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire; Eſſex; Ile of Eley; Cambridge-ſhire; Suffolke, Norfolk;</hi> in the <hi>North parts;</hi> and finally in moſt ſhires of this Realme. In thoſe daies they did abound, &amp; were gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to ſuch a number, as the diſplayer of the <hi>Secte</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered <hi>howe his heart did rue to ſpeake that which one of the ſame ſocietie did auouch to him for truth</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Diſplay pref.</note>, <hi>Not a fewe Ministers of the ſimple ſort were with</hi> H. N. <hi>his fancies entangled: nor the chiefeſt place of the Realme free from theſe men</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Ibid. E. <hi>4.</hi> a.</note>. Since, that they are diminiſhed, I heare not; but them to bee hugely encreaſed, through rufull conniuence, I haue arguments to thinke: but that their encreaſe may be hindered, I hope authoritie will take order.</p>
               <p>They ſay they are alſo poore, or the moſt of them: but if the booke of their names, called of them <hi>The booke of Life,</hi> could be ſeene, it would then appeare, I doubt not, that both the number of them is great, and moſt of them very rich.</p>
               <p>It is further obſerued, that thoſe poore ones which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer impriſonment any where for <hi>H. N.</hi> and his <hi>Seruice,</hi> are well maintained while they are in durance: which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth that good contributions among them are made for the ſupportation of their Secte, which cannot be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med without good ſtore of wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Family of Loue.</head>
               <p>OSacred Prince, we humbly pray,<note place="margin">Their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> that the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie will mooue your Princely heart with true iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15022:31"/>to diſcerne betwixt the right &amp; wrong of our cauſe, according to that moſt certaine, and Chriſtian rule ſet downe by our Sauiour Chriſt vnto his diſciples <hi>(Math. 7.12)</hi> Yee ſhall know the tree by his fruites; and in our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, peaceable, and honeſt liues, and conuerſation to protect vs, and in our diſobedience, and miſdemeanor to puniſh vs as reſiſters of Gods ordinance, or the kingly au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, &amp; moſt high office of iuſtice committed vnto your Maieſtie to that purpoſe towards your ſubiects. <hi>Rom. 13.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>THey woulde inſinuate into his Maieſties heart how they are <hi>The good trees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In their <hi>Courtly deuice,</hi> they ſay, that the onely diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt them, and the learned Preachers (whom they take of all others to be their moſt capitall enemies) is, That what the ſaid Preachers do ſay, <hi>The Familists de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to doe:</hi> as if they onely and none beſides, had a deſire to doe the will of God.</p>
               <p>But what ſpeake I of deſiring to do Gods will? They do it indeed, and really perform it. <hi>For they cannot bring-foorth any thing elſe, but all good, and Loue</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Docum. ſent. c. <hi>2. §. 1.</hi>
                  </note>; <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is able to plucke them from the Word, nor to make them conſent to any euill, or vanitie</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 13. §. 5.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That which they know not in the death, is now appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them in euerlaſting Life. The death is nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſwallowed vp in the death; the euerlaſting Life is come vnto them in the Renewing of their Life. The Hell is iudged or condemned to the pit of Hell: The Heauen is ſhewed vnto them in the heauenly Being or forme</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Spir. Land. c. 44. §. 10.12.</note>.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:15022:31"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>They are come to the Reſt of all the Holy ones and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God; and euen ſo they eate of the wood of life which ſtandeth in the middeſt of the pleaſant garden, and liue eternally</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 55. §. 9.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They are ſubiect to no Gods, nor lawes, or Ceremonies, but onely to the Lord their God, and to his moſt-holy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Loue. They are not likewiſe ſubiect in bondage vnto the Creatures, neither yet to any created thing, but only to the Creator &amp;c. All their Life, Minde, and delight on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is in God, and God himſelfe likewiſe, with his mind, Life, or Spirit, is in them: and they are euen ſo of one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie or ſubſtance with each other (namely God, and his people of peace</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 40. §. 1.2.18.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is no wickedneſſe, nor malicious Imaginations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, neither yet viſion of euill</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 33. §. 9.</note>. <hi>Holie, &amp; good, are pure are all their workes and thoughts</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 34. §. 11.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They are Gods habitation</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">1. <hi>Exhort. c.</hi> 12. §. 38. <hi>c.</hi> 20. §. 7.</note>, <hi>the ſeale of Gods Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Proph. of the Spir. c. <hi>7. §. 15.</hi>
                  </note>; <hi>God his Saints</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 19. §. 14.</note>; <hi>his acceptable people</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">Fidel. decl. c. <hi>4. §. 11.</hi>
                  </note>; <hi>the children of the kingdome</hi>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">Spir. land. preſ. <hi>§. 7.</hi>
                  </note>; <hi>the holy Cittie of peace, the new</hi> Ieruſalem <hi>deſcended from Heauen</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 17.</note>; <hi>the reſt of all the Saints or children of GOD</hi>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">Cri. voice. cap. <hi>1. §. 1.3.</hi>
                  </note>; <hi>the bodie of Chriſt</hi>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 3. §. 2.</note>; <hi>one with GOD, and GOD one with them</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">Spir land c. <hi>36. §. 1.</hi>
                  </note>; <hi>they are riſen from the death, with the Reſurrection of the Righteous, in the euerlaſting Life, and liue eternally</hi>
                  <note n="(r)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 37. §. 2.</note>.</p>
               <p>Infinite ſuch words, and places from themſelues, and their <hi>H. N.</hi> might be alledged, or ſhewe the heauenly condition of theſe, aboue all other men: iuſtifying his Maieſties words altogether, that they are <hi>a vile Sect,</hi> thinking themſelues onely pure, and in a manner (yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together many of them) without ſinne, the onely true Church, and only worthy to be participant of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15022:32"/>and all the reſt of the world, to be but abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſight of God: and ſo rightly, properly, and principally the moſt odious <hi>Puritans</hi> vnder the coape of Heauen.</p>
               <p>The Almightie, and all-prouident God, which hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired his Maieſtie with the bleſſed gift of diſcerning ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, enhable his Maieſtie with ſpirit and vertue from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, that hee may remoue theſe ſtumbling blockes, and cauſes of diuiſion if they will not repent, and both in heart and hand ioyne with his Church and people. For, <hi>hee beareth not the ſword in vaine.</hi> Rom. 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>AND gratious Soueraigne, wee humbly beſeech your Highneſſe, with Princely regard in equitie &amp; fauour to pouder and grant the humble ſute contained in this moſt lowely ſupplication of your loyall, true harted, faithful, &amp; afflicted ſubiects; &amp; to remember that your Maieſtie, in your book of Princely, graue, &amp; fatherly aduiſe to the happie Prince, your Royal Sonne, doth conclude, that <hi>Principis eſt parcere ſubiectis, &amp; debellare ſuperbos;</hi> and then to doubt, God will bleſſe your Highneſſe, and all your noble off-ſpring with peace, long life, and all honors and happineſſe, long to continue, and raigne ouer vs. For the which we will euer pray with inceſſant prayers to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>HITHERTO in their Supplication, the <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes</hi> haue quarrelled with his Maieſtie for calling
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15022:32"/>them <hi>Puritanes;</hi> they haue callenged his Highneſſe of vntrueth, as vttering that in a publike writing againſt them, which neither himſelfe is able to iuſtifie, nor any indifferent man, dare auouch; they confeſſe further they haue by them, and haue reade certaine bookes which the royall and ſupreame authoritie of this Realme hath prohibited them either to reade, or haue; they haue commended to the Starres that monſter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men <hi>H.N.</hi> both for his heauenly vocation, calling, Office, bookes, and writinges, which not onely all the learned and godly Prelates and Preachers, but the whole Church of England, yea all Churches Chriſtian (as moſt impious and Antichriſtian) vtterly condemne; they haue intimated that neither his Maieſtie, nor his people, vnleſſe they ſubmitte themſelues vnto the <hi>Seruice of Loue,</hi> deuiſed by <hi>H. N.</hi> ſhall be ſaued; they haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticed his Highneſſe to read and peruſe bookes both poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonfull and dangerous, they haue condemned all other men in this Realme, not ſiding with them, as curſed, and vnfruitefull trees; and all this willingly &amp; ſtudiouſly, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly, and apparantly they haue done, the leaſt of theſe crimes deſeruing royall indignation in an hie degree. Now what doth our <hi>Familie?</hi> Craue they pardon meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at his Maieſties hands for theſe their offences, audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly committed? Noe ſuch thing; yea they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in their diſloyall courſe, boldely crauinge, though with humble wordes, yet with proud hearts, what they haue ſued for, may readily bee graunted them.</p>
               <p>Yea as earſt, ſo here they both ſet out themſelues, as ſubmiſſe, and duetifull ſubiectes, condemning all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, eſpecially their aduerſaries as proude, and wiſhing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15022:33"/>puniſhment vnto them, and aduancement with fauour vnto themſelues; yea they let not to ſay how his Maieſty may feare great plagues to light vpon him, if hee puniſh them; but ſhall bee ſure both hee and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, of longe life, much proſperitie, and eternall happineſſe, if he ſhewe fauour to the <hi>Familie of Loue,</hi> and their cauſe.</p>
               <p>A graceleſſe, and audacious companie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Familie of Loue.</head>
               <p>MOſt-gratious Soueraigne,<note place="margin">Their Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</note> here followeth the briefe reherſall, and Confeſſion of the Chriſtian Beliefe and religion of the company that are named the Familie of Loue. Which (for the cauſes therein ſpecified) was by them ſet out in print about that time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were firſt perſecuted &amp; impriſoned in this Realme for the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, by their aforeſaid aduerſaries, and by meanes of their falſe accuſations and complaints vnto the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates againſt them: the which we haue thought neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to preſent here with vnto your Maieſtie, for that you may therby the better vnderſtand of our innocent intent and profeſſion whatſoeuer you ſhall heare reported to the contrarie by our enimies, or by any that be ignorant ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: humblie beſeeching your Highneſſe to vouchſafe to read the ſame, and with your vnpartiall and godly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to conſider, and iudge of vs and our cauſe in equitie, and fauour accordinglie, till your Maieſtie ſhall haue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true intelligence thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:15022:33"/>
               <head>The Examination.</head>
               <p>THe confeſſion here mentioned, and tendered, (as they ſaie) I neuer ſawe: yet haue I heard well there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. It was publiſhed in the yeare of our Lord. 1575.</p>
               <p>That ſo long ago, or ſince, the <hi>Familie of Loue,</hi> were perſecuted, and impriſoned for the ſame <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> or profeſſing the ſame, is both an egregious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, a ſlander of the State, and a falſe informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>It is obſerued concerning <hi>H. N.</hi> that, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating of his <hi>Loue Seruice,</hi> hee hath bookes of ſundry natures, and ſorts; ſome for <hi>Nouices,</hi> &amp; wel-willing ones, and ſome for the elder ſort, grown into the manly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the <hi>Familie</hi> myſteries.</p>
               <p>Of the former be <hi>N. N.</hi> his <hi>Inſtructions of the vpright Faith, and chriſtian Baptiſme; his Crying voice; his Firſt exhortation,</hi> and ſuch like, which may bee confeſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>adulterous, and ſinnefull generation, and the falſe hearts of the Scripture learned</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>H. N.</hi> 1. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort. c. 6. §. 5.7.8.9.</note>.</p>
               <p>The latter ſort containe the <hi>Loue</hi> ſecretes or priuie myſteries communicable only with ſuch as are come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>the manly age, and haue Beards</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>H. N.</hi> Prou. c. 21. § 1.</note>, <hi>and ſit vpon the ſeates of the Elders, or wiſe, and daiely heare the ſecret myſteries of all matters</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Ibid. §. 2.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yee ſhall not talke of your Secrets (either yet vtter your myſteries) openly, or nakedly</hi> (ſaith <hi>H. N.</hi> vnto theſe <hi>Familiſts</hi>) <hi>in the hearing of your young children, and diſciples; but ſpare them not</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>in the Eares, or hearing of the Elders, which can vnderſtand the ſame, and are able to beare, or away with the ſound thereof. For
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15022:34"/>it is giuen to the Elders to vnderſtand the priuie my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the wiſe, and to expounde their para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Ibid. c. 22. §. 15.</note>.</p>
               <p>So theſe Companions, this <hi>Familie of Loue,</hi> they haue among them good bookes after the Scripture learning, common with vs, and agreeable to the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on profeſſed by his Maieſtie, and ratified by the lawes of this Realme; and they haue alſo the workes, and bookes of <hi>H. N. Elidad, Fidelitas,</hi> and other <hi>Familie Elders,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining the found and Chriſtian doctrine compriſed in the Confeſſion mentioned. This Confeſſion of theirs, or ours rather, they <hi>waus</hi> about (which worde <hi>H. N.</hi> vſeth, in ſcorne of our Confeſſions and religion)<note n="(e)" place="margin">Spirit. land. cap. <hi>5. §. 5.</hi>
                  </note>, as Children doe their Banners, when they are at play; but <hi>H. N.</hi> and their <hi>Familie Elders</hi> books are they which they only ſtudie, read at their meetings, delight in, and practice.</p>
               <p>Beſides which both Confeſſion of ours, and bookes of <hi>H. N.</hi> and ſuch Illuminates: they haue their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles, verball traditions, vnwritten or vnprinted verities, and priuate exercices, through which they <hi>growe vp in the Loue, according to the Requiring of her Seruice</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Elidads exhort. § 5.</note>, <hi>where all things needfull to be knowen, or declared, are alwaies, according to the capacitie of their vnderſtanding, brought and declared vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Ibid. §. 17.</note>; <hi>viz. vnto the young or newborne Children, according to their yongneſſe; vnto the weake, according to their weakeneſſe; vnto the ſtronge vp-growing Men, according to their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie or ſtrength; and vnto the Elders, according to their Dayednes, or olde age</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Ibid. §. 18.</note> where neither ſome heart <hi>All,</hi> nor all heare <hi>ſome ſecrets</hi> or priuie myſteries of their <hi>Sect.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:15022:34"/>
               <p> It is not for the confeſſion here ſpoken of: it is for <hi>H. N.</hi> and other <hi>Familie</hi> books which they detaine by them, and ſtudie, and for their vnlawfull <hi>Loue</hi> exerciſes and meetinges, that they are troubled: let them leaue, burne, or deface theſe bookes of <hi>H. N.</hi> and cleaue vnto this Confeſſion, and then without farther moleſtation, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, or perſecution, they may enioy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, and liberties of his Maieſties good ſubiects: which that they may doe, is mine hartie deſire and prayer vnto Almightie GOD.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
